<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A defence and true declaration of the thinges lately done in the lowe countrey, whereby may easily be seen to whom all the beginning and cause of the late troubles and calamities is to be imputed. And therewith also the sclaunders wherewith the aduersaries do burden the churches of the lowe countrey are plainly confuted..</title>
            <title>Libellus supplex Imperatoriae Majestati caeterisque sacri imperii electoribus, principibus, atque ordinibus nomine Belgarum ex inferiore Germania, Evangelicae religionis causa per Albani Ducis tyrannidem ejectorum in comitiis spirenibus exhibitus. English.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1571</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 192 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 77 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B00458</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18441</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S94277</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">56572897</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 56572897</idno>
            <idno type="VID">180997</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B00458)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 180997)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2152:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A defence and true declaration of the thinges lately done in the lowe countrey, whereby may easily be seen to whom all the beginning and cause of the late troubles and calamities is to be imputed. And therewith also the sclaunders wherewith the aduersaries do burden the churches of the lowe countrey are plainly confuted..</title>
                  <title>Libellus supplex Imperatoriae Majestati caeterisque sacri imperii electoribus, principibus, atque ordinibus nomine Belgarum ex inferiore Germania, Evangelicae religionis causa per Albani Ducis tyrannidem ejectorum in comitiis spirenibus exhibitus. English.</title>
                  <author>Newcomen, Elias, 1550?-1614.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[148] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Daye dwelling ouer Aldersgate.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1571].</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Initials; black letter.</note>
                  <note>Translation by Elias Newcomen, of Libellus supplex Imperatoriae Majestati nomine Belgarum ex inferiore Germania, Evangelicae religionis causa per Albani Ducis tyrannidem ejectorum.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [hand]⁴ **²⁻⁸ A²⁻⁸ B-H⁸ (**₁ and A₁ blank?).</note>
                  <note>Dedication signed by the translator: Elias Newcomen.</note>
                  <note>"Cum gratia &amp; Priuilegio Regiæ Maiestatis."</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: cropped, with loss of text, possibly also date from t.p.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Alba, Fernando Alvarez de Toledo, --  duque de, 1507-1582 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Inquisition --  Netherlands --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Persecution --  Netherlands --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  Wars of Independence, 1556-1625 --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:180997:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A DEFENCE <hi>and true declaration of the</hi>
               </hi> thinges lately done in the lowe countrey, whereby may eaſily be ſeen to whom all the beginning and cauſe of the late troubles and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities is to be imputed.</p>
            <p>And therewith alſo the ſclaunders wherewith the aduerſaries do burden the Churches of the lowe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey are plainly confuted.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. XLIII.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Geue ſentence with me (O God) and defend my cauſe againſt the vngodly people: O deliuer me from the deceitfull and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked man. For thou art the God of my ſtrength.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>AT LONDON. Printed by Iohn Daye dwelling ouer Alderſgate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>¶Cum gratia &amp; Priuilegio Regio Maieſtatie</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:180997:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:180997:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:180997:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:180997:3"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>To the right honorable and my ſingular good Lord and patrone the Lord Cheyne.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y ſingular good Lorde. The doynges of Papiſtes ſtandyng wholly, as theyr religion doth, vpon falſhed and crueltie, and taking to themſelues by vſe a licence of vntrue ſpeaking &amp; wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng, playnly ſheweth what fayth is to be geuen to ſuch as thinke them ſelues bounde to keepe no fayth. Such hath euer bene theyr maner, not onely in diſſimulation &amp; practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng before things be brought to paſſe, but al ſo in ſhameles lyeng and miſreporting them after they be ended. For what els is to be lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked for of that vnfaithful faith that is groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded wholly vpon falſhead and blaſphemie, is purſued wholly with malice and treaſon, is auaunced wholly by crueltie and tyranny, and hauyng no reſpect of proſperitie beyond this life, hath by confidence in man deſtroyed the feare of God?</p>
            <p>What maruell is it then if ſuch kynde of men, Monkes, Friers, and other Paraſites, hauing bene writers of hyſtories heretofore, haue filled the world with fayned miracles and with intolerable abſurdities, to flatter Popes and deceiue the people haue ſclande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb facs="tcp:180997:4"/>
Emperours Kynges and Princes, and as ordinarely layd vp in their Libraries falſe treatiſes and Chronicles to beguile poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, as in their cofers forged euidences which they dayly made to robbe true owners of their inheritaunce. In theſe falſities they ſo farre proceded, that their impudencie fallyng with want of ſhame by vſe of lyeng into ſo great imprudence as that manifeſt contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and inconueniences conuinced them, they then reſorted to iuſtifie their vntruthes &amp; ſeducyng the world with pretenſe of a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable deceiuyng men with godly errour. Surely whoes conſcience can ſerue them to do murders, to tumble vp kyngdomes, and rayſe all kynd of horrible and tragical exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, will not much ſticke to tell lyes in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſyng or reportyng the doinges of them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, and their aduerſaries. For <hi>Ex ijſdem ſunt &amp; nutriuntur mixta,</hi> a ſect patched vp of lyes muſt be fed and mainteyned with the ſame. Much lyke it is to the doyng of kyng <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard</hi> &amp; <hi>Cateſbie</hi> to bleare the worldes eyes with the proclamation of treaſon ſuppoſed to haue bene intended by the Lord Haſtings and <hi>Shores</hi> wife, and ſhewyng out his owne withered arme, after the example of <hi>Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninus Caracalla</hi> concerning his brother <hi>Geta,</hi> and ſuch like. So dyd that honeſt man <hi>Boner</hi> immediatly vppon the death of the excellent Martyr the Archebyſhop of Caunterbury o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly cauſe to be publiſhed in Print a report
<pb facs="tcp:180997:4"/>
of the Archbyſhops death and his woordes before hys death, directly contrarie to that which was ſpoken, and all in fauor of Papi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrie. Thence came it that all foreine hyſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries are at this day ſo ſtuffed with ſclanders agaynſt our eſtates people and Princes, ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſins that kyng <hi>Henrie</hi> the viij. reſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med his lawfull iuriſdiction from vſurpyng Popes. Our kynges be villanouſly termed tyrauntes, vertuous Queenes and Ladyes defamed, Nobilitie diſgraced, Parlamentes deſpiſed, the people reprochfully taunted, theeues, whoremongers, ſodomites, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers, and traytors ſainted, victories pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, factes and ſucceſſes falſly vttered, and that ſo playnly euen while lyuyng witneſſes preſent and parties to the maters them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues are hable truely to diſproue them. And all this they do vpon truſt that though it be ſome ſhame a while, yet theyr bookes ſhall ouerlyue mens perſons, and ſo at length de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue poſteritie: and ſo thinke they it reaſon now that other papiſtes hereafter ſhold en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioye the fruite of their falſhed at this tyme, as they haue the frute of other Papiſtes falſe hed heretofore. So doth fabulous Iouius, So doth pratyng Paradine, ſo doth the whole heape of Popiſh Pamphleters, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reuerence of Princes eſtates or of other mens eares, of their owne outworne hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties. This hath made common lyers to ſhew aduiſes of newes from beyond ſeas ſo
<pb facs="tcp:180997:5"/>
freſhly arriued that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> very inke blotted whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the letters were ſhewed in Paules, men ſurely worthy of their card couſin to hang on their backes to warne them, and F. cudgell better to aduiſe them. This doyng of theirs hath of late yeares continually enforced no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Princes and good men to publiſh Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logies and ſet foorth bookes to yeld true ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt of theyr factes agaynſte this poyſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous kynde of Paraſites and rumor ſprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. This, my Lord, hath cauſed the noble men and other of baſe Germanie to publiſh in Supplication by them exhibited to the Emperour the Electors and other Princes aſſembled at Spires, the report of theyr do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inges and ſufferynges, with requeſt of good interpretation and charitable ayde. Bicauſe the ſame conteineth a great deale of mater of good hyſtoricall knowlege, and bicauſe the dayly rumors of Papiſtes do amplifie euils to kyndle vncharitableneſſe agaynſt poore men, I haue thought good to turne the ſame into Engliſh, and to ſet it out to the world to behold, without preiudicing the credit of any, but leauyng euery man to beleue ſo far with them or agaynſt them as euident truth &amp; apparant proues ſhall leade them. Onely this by the way remembred, that the publike miniſters, embaſſadors, meſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers &amp; agentes for thoſe againſt whom theſe do complayne, haue not ſticked agaynſt common fayth to be certifiers and auouchers of vntruthes and
<pb facs="tcp:180997:5"/>
parteners of treaſons agaynſte our noble Queene, as in publike arrainementes and other open places and doynges, beſide ſecret knowledges, hath lately appeared.</p>
            <p>Hauyng performed this worke of tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation for credit of truth, and for rayſing of good affections in iuſt and indifferent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and for a good monument of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege to ſuch as lacke helpe of the Latin tong, wherin &amp; in the Dutche tong it hath ben be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore printed, I thought it my dutie to offer the ſame to your good Lordſhyp. Wherunto many reaſonable reſpectes hath moued me. Firſt your zeale to true Religion, your ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous gouernaunce of your houſehold ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, your noble and ſincere adminiſtration of iuſtice, without vſyng the Queene ſeruice to priuate malice and affections, and your ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere lookyng to daungerous cariers of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>true rumors and ſeditious ſpeeches in your countrey, all which vertues become a perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage fitte to receiue a worke intended for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of truth and confutation of ſclan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. Beſide that I beyng ſuſteined in ſtudie by your Lordſhyps liberalitie, do owe you that dutie that vnder your name ſhould paſſe to the worldes commoditie ſuch frutes of learnyng as I haue bene hable to yeld, humbly praying your Lordſhyp to accept the ſame, and moſt humbly beſechyng God long to bleſſe your Lordſhyp and my good Ladie, long in honor and proſperitie to ſerue
<pb facs="tcp:180997:6"/>
our moſt gracious Queene, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God long defend to hys honor and the ſuccour of hys Church, and comfort of her owne conſcience in not omittyng any thyng to the helpe of Gods flocke, and ſure remouyng of Gods enemyes dangerous practiſers, that as her preſent gouernement miniſtreth aboundance of good frutes, ſo the tymes imminent and poſteritie may find no lacke, but for her good prouiſions yeld her eternall thankefull memorie, when God ſhall haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued her as hys faythfull ſeruaunt to eternall bleſſed kyngdome.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your L. moſt humble Elias Newcomen.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:180997:6"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſame tempeſt, moſt victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Emperor and moſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Princes, which now almoſt a whole hundred yeares hath troubled ſundry partes of Europe, hath now alſo at this time by moſt cruell ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannie enforced vs being ſpoyled of our goods, chaſed out of our natiue contreyes, oppreſſed with ſclanders of our aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and toſſed with all kinde of calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, to flée as moſt humble ſuters to your clemencie for ſuccor.</p>
            <p>For we ſuppoſe there is no man igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, that long agoe Spaine, and ſince alſo by litle and litle a great part of all Europe not onely hath flamed with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward contentions and tumultes, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo hath in maner ben ouerwhelmed with moſt greuous ſtorme of perſecutions and tyrannie. Wherby certaine idle men which in onely name and outward ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture profeſſed a ſolitarie life ſeuered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all gouernance of common weales, and onely addicted to the preaching of the worde of God or quiet ſtudie of holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, haue begonne to créep into courtes of Kinges and Princes, and couering their greedy affections with cloke of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,
<pb facs="tcp:180997:7"/>
to miniſter ſuch counſells wherby they might by their new deuiſed meane of Inquiſition againſt hereſie, drawe to themſelues from the ciuile magiſtrate the hearing and iudgement of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſies of greateſt weight and impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. And ſo by litle and litle they haue atteined not onely by ſearching and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring to become Lordes of euery pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate perſons goods, poſſeſſions, houſes and moſt ſecrete places, yea and their wiues and children, but alſo to bring the magiſtrates and Princes themſelues in ſubiection to their authoritie. In what places they perceaued their deſires to be hindred either by the auncient liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the people, or by the diſcretion of the Rulers and Princes, ſtraightway they charged ſuch with forged ſclander of hereſie and rebellion, and ſo greuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enflamed the hartes of Kinges and Emperors againſt their ſubiectes. And by thys craftie meane they haue ſtirred vp ciuile diſſentions, tumultes of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monalties, and oftentimes gréeuous warres, whereby they haue brought moſt floriſhing contreyes into great diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb facs="tcp:180997:7"/>
and hatred of all kinges, princes, and nations, and ſo drawen them to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme calamitie.</p>
            <p>This, if any prouince in Europe hath euer felte, ſurely our contrey, namely that part of baſe Germanie that is ſubiecte to the moſt mighty king of Spaine, hath and ſpecially at thys time to their great deſtruction moſt miſerably ſuffred. For ſince that by the moſt falſe ſclanders and other cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt craftye meanes of the Spaniſhe Inquiſitors, thys countrey hath vnder pretenſe of hereſie and impietie, bene brought in greuous diſpleaſure with the Emperor Charles the fifth of hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pye memorie, and his ſonne Philippe King of Spaine and Lorde of baſe Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manie, and oppreſſed with moſt hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Edictes about religion procured by guile and ſclanderous report, and ſo hath of their great truth and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to their ſoueraigne Lordes now more than fiftie yeares with incredible pacience borne the Inquiſitors moſt cruell yoke, and now at length after matters in other countreyes adioyning
<pb facs="tcp:180997:8"/>
well ſettled to peace and quietneſſe, and the truth of the cauſe commonly diſclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, hoped to finde ſome releaſe of ſo great calamitie: it is now come to paſſe that the aduerſaries being greued to ſee them aſpire to ſuch libertie of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion as by thys time floriſhed not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in Germanie but alſo in Fraunce and many other places, haue in ſtrange maner and with moſt earneſt ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour trauailed, not onely to fruſtrate the hope of the inhabitantes, but alſo by bringing in a farre more greuous tyrannie, to pull from them all the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidue of their right and libertie that they had remayning: and ſo to ſpoile ſuch wealthy ones of their goods, and ſuch noble and mighty ones of their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues as they ſaw to be of habilitie to withſtand their attemptes.</p>
            <p>Therefore adioyning to them the Biſhop of Rome, and hauing obtained hys Bull, they did by ſondry ſclanders and with extreme importunacie wreſte from the King an Edicte agaynſt all the Priuileges of the contrey, agaynſt their lawes, ordinaunces, and aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
<pb facs="tcp:180997:8"/>
liberties, namely, for the preciſe obſeruing of the decrées of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of Trent, and for bringing in of new Biſhops, that ſhoulde put in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution throughout the whole land a new forme of Inquiſition, farre more cruell than the very Spaniſhe Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition which was firſt inuented againſt Iewes and Mahometane Apoſtataes, and ſo in ſhort time ſhould openly bring a moſt floriſhing and frée Prouince in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the moſt diſhonourable ſeruage of ſtraungers, and thoſe moſt villanous and abhominable perſons, to torment at their pleaſure the honeſteſt and beſt men vpon ſuborning of any infamous informer, or moſt corrupt witneſſe, with bondes, with racke, with gallowes and with fire, to thruſt the wealthy out of their poſſeſſions, to ſubdue the magiſtrates them ſelues to their iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, and to make themſelues Lordes of all, &amp; ſpecially to deſtroy vtterly and with moſt exquiſite torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes to murder and roote vp all thoſe that refuſed to obey the Biſhop of Romes power, and would haue their conſciences ſubiecte
<pb facs="tcp:180997:9"/>
to the onely worde of God contayned in the bookes of the olde and new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament.</p>
            <p>This matter geuing iuſt occaſion to the Nobilitie that they exhibited ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication for ſtaye thereof to the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſſe of Parma Regent there for the King, and in the ſame declared what calamitie would thereof vndoubtedly enſue: and likewiſe whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the commonal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie hauing heretofore vſed their religion within their priuate houſes, and ſeing the ſame thereby ſubiecte to ſclanders and enuie, did now by laying it open in publike preachinges and aſſemblies to the indifferent iudgement and exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of all good men, deliuer it from falſe and cauillous reportes: it came to paſſe that the aduerſaries here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon tooke occaſion by raiſing of ſondry tumultes moſt hatefully to incenſe the King againſt the whole people, as gil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the moſt haynous crimes of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie, rebellion, ſedition, and treaſon againſt God and the King. And where his maieſtie was fully determined to come into the lowe conteyr and him
<pb facs="tcp:180997:9"/>
ſelfe in perſon to heare the cauſe, and to end the whole matter according to right and equitie, they partly by ſut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle crafty meanes and very traitorous practiſes purpoſely deuiſed for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the people of that contrey, and partly by the importunate labour and impudent gredy endeuour of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine perſons, and partly alſo by ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſes and threatninges procured from forene partes, euen in maner againſt his will brought hym to thys that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing greuouſly incenſed agaynſt his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes, ſodeinly altering hys former purpoſe, he ſent thether in hys ſtede with moſt large Commiſſion to heare the cauſe and diſpoſe of the ſtate of the common weale, the Duke of <hi>Alua</hi> a man both a moſt aſſured miniſter of their Inquiſition, and for olde grudges a moſt bitter enemie to the Princes and ſtate of the lowe contrey.</p>
            <p>He coloring hys owne malitious affections with the glorious pretenſe of zele to reſtore the Romiſhe religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and to chaſtiſe Rebells, it is incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible to tell how great and how out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious
<pb facs="tcp:180997:10"/>
crueltie he hath echewhere ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted vpon the poore inhabitantes of the lowe contrey, without reſpecte or difference: by how many and how ſtrange deuiſes he hath robbed all mens goods: how he hath ſpoyled the whole Prouince of all their ornamentes, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>armed them of their defences, depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued them of their liberties, and ſtrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped them out of their lawes and priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leges: how euery honeſt man he hath condemned by priuate warrant with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out iudiciall order, euery the moſt inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent mans bloud he hath ſhed, euery moſt vertuous perſon he hath put to moſt vile ſhame, all lawes of God and man he hath violated, the bandes of mariage he hath broken, the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Baptiſme he hath polluted, all order of charitie and frendly ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie he hath ouerthrowen; finally no part of moſt extreme crueltie and ſuch as neuer was heard of before hath he omitted. And yet in the meane time he ceaſeth not to throw vpon vs the blame of his haynous factes, and by procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations publiſhed &amp; by infamous libels
<pb facs="tcp:180997:10"/>
printed openly to all princes and ſtates to accuſe vs of moſt greuous crimes, for thys onely cauſe forſooth that in fléeing we gaue place to his furie, and by the helpe of Gods protection haue eſcaped his ſworde moſt thirſty of our bloudes.</p>
            <p>All which thinges, foraſmuch as almighty God hath ſo determined that we ſhoulde for a time be here afflicted by the tyrannie of the wicked, we woulde haue thought it beſt for vs to paſſe ouer in ſilence and in pacience, and to waite for the time which the great Iudge hath appointed, either for bringing our innocencie to knowledge, or for opening the eyes and eares of our King to vnderſtand our vniuſte miſerie and iuſte complaint, were it not that we doe plainly ſée that ſuch our ſilence, ſpecially in thys ſo ſacred and ſo full aſſemblie of your maieſtie moſt victorious Emperour, and of your highneſſes moſt noble Princes, might hereafter bring no ſmall preiudice to vs and our innocencie before ſuch to whom the truth ſhall not be ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently
<pb facs="tcp:180997:11"/>
knowen. For by ſuch meane the ſonne of God Ieſus Chriſt him ſelfe, and his doctrine which we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe according to hys worde, ſhoulde become ſubiecte to the moſt haynous ſclanders of the aduerſaries, as if the profeſſors thereof before thys ſo reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend iudgement ſeate of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, before ſo vpright and vncorrupt iudges, before thys theatre ſo furniſhed with ſo great aſſemblie of ſondry na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, were by ſilent confeſſion found gilty, not onely of hereſie and peſtilent vngodly error, but alſo of ſhamefull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, of wicked ſedition and diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance of common peace.</p>
            <p>Wherefore we haue vtterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined, that we can not with good peace of conſcience longer kepe ſilence. But for aſmuch as we know that the order of theſe vſuall aſſemblies of the ſtates of the ſacred Empyre haue their chiefe reſpecte to this end, that ſuch as be oppreſſed by force and iniurie may heare preſent their compleintes as to the chiefe throne of Iuſtice in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome: we thought it our duetie
<pb facs="tcp:180997:11"/>
to declare our whole eſtate to your ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie moſt mightye Emperour and to your highneſſes moſt noble Princes, and to open vnto you the very originall fountaines of thys our moſt greuous calamitie, that if the mercie of God haue decréed to make an end of our ſo great miſeries we may by your good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and liberalitie beginne to take breath agayne after thys moſt heauy weight of oppreſſion: If not, yet the cauſe being more throughly heard, we ſhall before indifferent iudges deliuer our innocencie from the moſt vniuſte ſclanders of our aduerſaryes. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, if nothing ells, yet thys we ſhall obtaine that from henceforth our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and the profeſſion of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell ſhall not beare the infamie of ſo greuous crimes with them that here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore being filled with the accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the aduerſaryes haue not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtoode the truth: and that Ieſus Chriſt the ſonne of God whoſe name we profeſſe ſhall not bee wounded through vs, and finally that we ſhall not as enemies of publike peace and
<pb facs="tcp:180997:12"/>
quietneſſe be expelled from common ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietie by forrene Princes and peoples which is the chiefe thinges that our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies doe ſéeke, but that the whole truth being throughly vnderſtoode, the whole originall of the miſchiefes ſhall be iuſtly layed vpon them that infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with their owne gredy malices do tumble vp all thinges, and ſuch good and innocent men as they haue by wrong and tyrannie ſpoyled of their goods and can not yet bereue of their liues, they labour to oppreſſe with moſt vile ſclaunderous reportes to your ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie O Emperor, and your highneſſes O noble Princes, that ſo they may drawe you into the fellowſhip of their crueltie, and by your helpe they may ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſatiſfie their vnſatiable thirſt with our bloud, or glutt their moſt bitter ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred that they haue conceaued againſt vs with our deſtruction.</p>
            <p>Which thing that they ſhall not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, your equitie, truth, and vpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and our innocencie, do aſſure vs. In confidence whereof we proſtrate vs at your feete, we flée to your protection
<pb facs="tcp:180997:12"/>
and mercy, &amp; craue helpe of your religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe iuſtice &amp; vprightneſſe: and we moſt humbly beſech you, that preſeruing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iuſtice of law, ye will vouchſafe moſt mercifully to defend our miſerable and afflicted innocencie aganiſt the outragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous power and vnbridled boldneſſe of our enemies.</p>
            <p>That ye may vnderſtand how iuſtly ye may do it, &amp; that ye may clerely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue in whom the fault of the whole miſchief reſteth, we beſech your maieſty moſt inuincible Emperor, &amp; your high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes moſt noble Princes, that at lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure ye will gently and diligently read this booke annexed to this our ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, wherin with the truth of the whole hiſtorie, we declare our innocencie to all men: and that with the ſame pacience and equitie of minde that you vſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue the complaintes of all miſerable and innocent perſons, it may pleaſe you alſo to vnderſtand our cauſe, and to your power deliuer vs out of theſe calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. So ſhall ye ſhew your ſelues wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy miniſters to the ſoueraigne king of kinges &amp; ſupreme iudge, and ſhall ſtirre vp our hartes to be continuall ſuters to his grace and mercy for you.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:180997:13"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:180997:13"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is now nere a hundred yeres agoe ſins the moſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Ferdinand and Iſabell Kyng and Quene of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtile,<note place="margin">The be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynnyng of the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition, and of the Inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors power in Spaine.</note> hauyng ended theyr great and long warre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the Mahumetanes which had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaded inhabited and trobled the kingdome of Spayne by the ſpace of almoſt viij. hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeres, and hauyng chaced the ſayd enemies out of all Spayne and recouered the kyngdome of Granada, gaue theyr mynde to ſtabliſh relligion, and to roote out all the remnantes of the wicked Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humetane and Iewiſh ſectes. The charge hereof was committed to the Freres of Dominikes ſect, whoe had wholly poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Kynges and Quenes hart, &amp; eares with a great eſtimation of holineſſe and wiſedome: and therewith was alſo geuen them full authoritie in all thynges that might ſeme requiſite to ſo great a mater. They ſuppoſing them ſelues to haue ſo obteined a moſt commodious occaſion to aduance their owne power and dignitie, perſuaded the Kyng and Quene that for atcheuyng therof a moſt extreme and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouable ſeneritie was neceſſarie. And as
<pb facs="tcp:180997:14"/>
though the dealing with religion perteined not to the ciuile magiſtrate, but proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly belonged to Friers whoe as it were by a peculiar name called them ſelues reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious men and to preſtes, they ſayd it was neceſſarie that a new court of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitors ſhould be erected, to whom not only the hearyng and determinyng of ſuch maters, but alſo the whole iugement of all religion whatſoeuer it were, ſhold with full power be committed. The well mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng Princes, which onely directed their intention, by any way howſoeuer it were, to auance the Chriſtian fayth light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gaue credit to thoſe whom they thought to excell other men in pureneſſe of life and holyneſſe, and therewith committed to thoſe them ſelues that were the inuenters therof the whole power of the Inquiſitors office to vſe accordyng to their owne diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion. Thereto was added the confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of pope Sixtus the fowerth then by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Rome. For he labored with all his endeuour and earneſt affection not onely to ſtabliſh but alſo to aduance and magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the fower orders of Freres then lately ſprong vp.</p>
            <p>To which his purpoſe he ſaw the zele
<pb facs="tcp:180997:14"/>
of the Kyng and Quene of Spayne to be a very fitt meane. Wherfore by his autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, which then was at the greateſt that euer it was ſins the world began, and by his Bull he confirmed and ratified this new iudiciall throne, and new kyngdome of Inquiſitors. So this power vpholden both by the Royall and papall authoritie, in ſhort tyme maruellouſly encreaſed. And ſithe there is no man whom the right order of religion concerneth not, by this pretenſe they eaſily got to them ſelues the iuriſdiction and iugement ouer all men of all eſtates and degrées And by this meane within ſhort while after, they began to be Lordes ouer all mens goodes, poſſeſſions, lyues and conſciences, till of vnmeaſura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble power aroſe in them pride and coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe, and conſequently therof grew the hatred of all men agaynſt them, ſo as now woman thought them any longer to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable. Therefore by the counſell and meanes of certaine biſhops and other of the clergie that were in great eſtimation and credit in Spayne, which repined to be ſubiect to the dominion of the Freres, it was procured that by the kynges autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie the power of Inquiſition was taken
<pb facs="tcp:180997:15"/>
from the Dominicanes and geuen to the clergie, and it was ordered that out of the byſhops and other preſtes ſhold be choſen the maiſters of the Inquiſition, which ſhold in dede vſe the trauaile and aduiſe of the Dominicanes, but yet ſhold ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue to them ſelues the ſoueraigne power of the Inquiſitors office. Theſe, either for that they had ſome feruent zele of religion, or for that they cunnyngly cloked their ambitious pride, partly with wonderfull opinion of holineſſe, partly by the fauor and power of Princes and men of great authoritie to whom they were ioyned in frendſhyp, kinne or alliance, partly alſo by corrupt and ſecret deuiſes, in ſhort tyme auaunced this their new raiſed empire to ſo great a heigth, that now they not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vſed dominion at their pleaſure ouer the commonaltie, but alſo brought into ſubie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the holy Inquiſition all the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of all the people, &amp; eſtates of the realme, they brake priuileges and immunities, they abated the dignitie of the Nobilitie whom they call <hi>The grand counſell</hi> with out whoes authoritie in time paſt nothing was decréed in Spayne: finally vnder pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſe of religion and ſeruice of God they
<pb facs="tcp:180997:15"/>
vſurped to them ſelues ſoueraigne power ouer the kyng hym ſelfe, and ouer the maieſtie of the royall ſcepter: all noble men and perſones of any credit whom they thought in any wiſe able to hynder their enterpriſes, they cauſed to be accuſed of hereſie and cruelly killed them, or defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced them with moſt reprochefull note of open ſhame, ſuch as ſhold remaine vpon al their poſteritie, and ſo made them infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous and of odious memorie for euer.</p>
            <p>Theſe deuiſes though to many men they ſemed ſtrange and intolerable, yet both bicauſe they were principally proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded agaynſt the moſt hatefull enemies of Spayne and of Chriſtian religion, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Mores, Mahumetanes and Iewes, and alſo for that they bleared moſt mens eyes with the pretenſe of Gods ſeruice and opinion of holineſſe, and finally for that they not a litle auailed to the enrichyng of the kynges treaſurie now greatly wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted with many warres, to whoes vſe the one moitie of the goodes of all perſones condemned was employed, they were dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly more and more ſtabliſhed by the earneſt fauors, authoritie and power of the moſt part of the mightieſt perſones and ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:180997:16"/>
of the Kyng and Quéene them ſelues, vntill the Arragonoyes whoe are the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall prouince of Spayne both in right of auncient libertie, in nobilitie, and large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of dominion, openly reſiſted. They, when they nothyng preuailed with kyng Ferdinand by humble and lowly petition, attempted by force and armes to kepe out this peſtilence from their contrey, for that they plainely ſaw that their libertie which they had receiued moſt large and incredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble from their aunceſters, and hetherto kept inuiolate ſhold by this meane be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, and that themſelues and all theirs ſhold be made ſubiect to the moſt diſhono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable tyrannie of the clergie. But they preuailed not. For after many trobles, much deſtruction and bloodſhed, they were compelled mawgre their willes and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force, as the reſidue of Spayne dyd, to yeld their neckes to ſtoope vnder this yoke of Inquiſition ſo that the ſame prouince, than which in tyme paſt there was none of more fréedome, is now in ſuch caſe as at this day there is none to be found in more ſeruitude &amp; ſubiection. By terror of which example, and by great opinion of holineſſe which the Inquiſitors had gotten by the
<pb facs="tcp:180997:16"/>
good ſucceſſe in this caſe, it came to paſſe that they ſubdued all Spayne vnto them without any further reſiſtance.</p>
            <p>But as the gredy deſires of men are naturally vnmeaſurable and vnſatiable,<note place="margin">The enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyng of the Inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</note> this luſt of dominion could not long be conteined within the boundes of Spayne though they be full large, but, ſtill forſoth with the ſame plauſible pretenſe of ſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyng religion they bent their mynde to enlarge their empire, and promiſed them ſelues the rule of the whole world. For there is ſcarcely any contrey which in ſhort ſpace folowyng they attempted not to make ſubiect to them, euen by the ſame ſuttle meanes wherby they had daunted Spaine. For they compelled both the chefe part of Italie and many iſlandes both of the Middland and Oceane ſeas, and Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land it ſelfe (though not for long tyme to yeld their neckes to this halter of Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition. Yea they not onely ranged ouer to the vttermoſt Indians, and to the farre di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantes landes ſeuered from vs by the huge ſtreame of the Ocean but alſo vnder pretenſe of orderyng religion they ſpoyled the poore and ſimple inhabitantes of thoſe contreyes of all their goods and poſſeſſions,
<pb facs="tcp:180997:17"/>
and of their wiues, children and liues, yea and cruelly lyke butchers tearyng them with all kinde of tormentes they ſlew them by heapes, and brought them to ſuch miſerie and wretched plight, that a great number of them choſe rather to ſlay them ſelues, than to come vnder ſuch cruell ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection of vnnaturall men. Yea not long agoe they employed all their counſelles &amp; all their practiſes, and left no way vnaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayed, to bryng whole Germanie in ſlaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie vnder the ſame yoke. And ſo farre with the authoritie and threateninges of the bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of Rome dyd they driue on the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour Charles the fift of famous memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie euen in a maner agaynſt his will and long witholding himſelfe, that the beſt and moſt noble princes he proclaimed trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and made moſt deadly warre vpon them as vpon ſworne enemies, and vnder the pretended cloke of rebellion armed the proteſtant princes the one agaynſt the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, he brought the frée cities into moſt diſhonorable ſlauerie of the Spaniſh ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diar, and made the maieſtie of the moſt noble and ſacred empire, ſubiect to the luſt and vntolerable deſires of moſt villanous perſones. Which moſt cruell yoke, if part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:180997:17"/>
the valeancie of the Germaine princes, and partly the equitie and gentle fauor of the Emperour him ſelfe at length percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the mater as truth was, had not ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of or taken away, whole Germanie might long ago haue ben in ſuch caſe as now is that parcell thereof from whenſe are now moſt vniuſtly baniſhed and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to ſue for and pleade, the cauſe of our afflicted contrey, oppreſſed not onely with moſt greuous tyranny, but alſo with moſt vnworthy ſclanders: and to proteſt before almightie God and all mankynde, that there is no other cauſe of our calamitie but euen the ſame which had nere ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed whole Germanie, namely the gredy ambition of theſe men that vnder pretenſe of ſtabliſhyng religion, labour to enlarge their dominion throughout the whole by right or wrong. And ſo much the more earneſtly they endeuour to bryng it into the low contrey of Germanie, bicauſe it is by allyance of the princes, by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munitie of one kyng, and by auncient en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercourſe of merchandiſe and conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſomewhat nerely conioyned vnto them, &amp; therfore of long tyme they thinke that they may lawfully enforce vpon vs
<pb facs="tcp:180997:18"/>
the Spaniſh lawes and ordinances, Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh maners and the Spaniſh yoke of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition, abrogatyng all our contrey lawes, aboliſhing all memorie of the Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane name, deſtroyeng our priuileges and oppreſſing our libertie.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſuttle meanes and deuiſes of the Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitors.</note>When they long ſins eſpied, that the contrey though it be not great, yet flori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth in wealth and power, and is ſo fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed agaynſt foreine force not onely with ſtrong townes and caſtelles, but alſo with good lawes and ordinances, &amp; with large priuileges prerogatiues immunities and other liberties, that ſo long as it hath her owne princes fauor, it is eaſily able to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend her auncient fréedome: they haue theſe many yeres euidently purpoſed and practiſed diuerſe wayes to bryng the inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitantes into ſuſpicion and diſpleaſure both with the Emperour Charles the fift and with kyng Philip his ſonne, to accuſe them for heretikes and rebelles, and ſo to perſuade to haue them eſtemed as ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies and traitors: that by this meane, the contrey which for many reſpectes they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compted moſt commodious for their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, might be ſpoyled of all right of liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, ſubdued, and added to their dominion.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:180997:18"/>Sometyme they pretended this color, that the ſeignories were to many and too ſeuerall, ſometime that in reſpect of the number of ſeignories, the lawes, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes, and ordinances were too diuerſe: ſometyme they alleged that the people were to wilde and proude by reaſon of their priuileges immunities and liberties, ſometime they brought the kyng in ialou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie of the too great wealth and power of his ſubiectes: ſometyme they informed that the entercourſe &amp; trafiques of foreine nations were ſuſpicious. Finally, they left nothyng vntryed that might any way ſeme to ſerue to agreue his minde toward them. Principally they vrged this one thyng that the auncient libertie of aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie of the eſtates in parlamentes that hath continued in all ages greatly abateth the power of the prince, for that their both by moſt auncient vſage of their forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers it was ſo prouided, and by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes and couenantes of the princes them ſelues co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmed with their othes it was ſo ordeined, that the princes ſhould not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crée or do any thyng to the preiudice of the peoples libertie or of the authoritie of their lawes without the will and aſſent of
<pb facs="tcp:180997:19"/>
the eſtates of the whole contrey: and that therefore they more regarded the actes of the Eſtates than the kings proclamations that they eſtemed the kyng not as a kyng but as ſome co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon Duke or Earle, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gardian of their right &amp; lawes, to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne the common weale not by his owne authoritie but after a preſcribed forme of lawes and the ordinances of the eſtates: moreouer that as it is in moſt frée commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> weales, ſo they yerely create of them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues magiſtrates,<note place="margin">Burrow-maiſters.</note> &amp; burrowmaſters with ſoueraine power of negatiue voyce: that ſtrangers are deharred from bearyng of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice in the common weale: &amp; eccleſiaſticall men by the lawes and ſtatutes of the land are excluded from power of iuriſdiction, &amp; ſo the way ſtopped vp for the princes ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt &amp; faithfulleſt ſeruantes to atteine any gouernement. Theſe and ſuch like things (ſay they) in tymes paſt haue often euen occaſion to the commonaltie proudely to diſobey the commaundement of theyr princes, yea &amp; to burden their Lordes and princes to lawes and conditions, yea and if their Princes attempted any thyng a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the vſage and will of the eſtates, they haue preſumed to chaſten them ſome
<pb facs="tcp:180997:19"/>
tyme with penalties, ſometyme with em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment, and ſometyme with depoſing them.<note place="margin">This appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth by the Spaniardes owne hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by Alfo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ. Vloa, and printed in Dutch at Dilling. For there they confeſſe that this was their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the whole con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey to a kyngdome like Sicile &amp; Naples.</note> Theſe thyngs (ſayd they) are not to be ſuffred of Princes. Therfore they long moſt earneſtly trauailed with Charles the Emperour, and with Philip his ſonne, that the whole contrey might be reduced into one bodie, and made ſubiect to one forme of lawes and iuriſdiction, &amp; brought to the name and title of a kyngdome, and that, abrogating the power of popular magiſtrates and lawes, it might be gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with new lawes by diſcretion as the kyngdomes of Sicile and Naples be, that haue bene atcheued by conqueſt. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in when they ſaw that they labored in vayne, both bicauſe the ſtates of all the townes moſt ſtrifly withſtode it, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happes alſo for that the Emperour hym ſelfe beganne to ſmell their ſiniſter pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes and vntrue meanyng, they differed that mater to a more commodious ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and this yet by the way with their importunate ſclanderous cauillynges they obteined, that afterward he wold neuer in any wiſe ſuffer the ſolemne parla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, or generall aſſemblies of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates of all the prouinces to be kept as it
<pb facs="tcp:180997:20"/>
had ben vſed in his progenitors tymes, and that he placed in gouernance Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call men and ſuch as not only by the law of God, the ciuile and canon lawes, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo by the auncient cuſtome of the contrey &amp; by ſondry decrées of the Dukes of Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gundie were excluded from iudiciall of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices and from bearyng ciuile rule in the common weale.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the Inquiſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictes in the low co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey.</note>Finally to make them ſelues in eaſier way to that dominion that they had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, vnder pretenſe of ſtabliſhyng reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, they with importunacie procured ſuch rigorouſneſſe of edictes agaynſt thoſe that profeſſed the doctrine of the Goſpell, as neuer any contrey, neuer any citie, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer any common weale had ſene before. For they had fully perſuaded hym,<note place="margin">The very wordes of the Edict, dated at wormes the 8. of May. 1521</note> as is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo conteined in the expreſſe wordes of the edict that Luther, whoes doctrine thoſe dyd follow, profeſſed the Pelagian error, ſet naught by all the holy fathers and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of the Church aboliſhed all Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, ouerthrew all ciuile gouernance and politike order, ſtirred vp the people to take armure, made them apt to murder, ſteale, waſt and deſtroy with fire, and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally gaue euery one leaue to lyue as he
<pb facs="tcp:180997:20"/>
lyſted.</p>
            <p>In the which Peter a Soto a Spaniard hys confeſſor, &amp; one of the maiſters of the Spaniſhe Inquiſition not of the meaneſt ſorte dyd further them verie much. By the whiche perſuaſion they eaſilie inforced the Emperour Charles a prince otherwiſe by nature gentle and mercifull, to decrée, and<note n="1" place="margin">That the aſſent of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates was not taken, it is manifeſt by the verie words of the Edictes, by the which the eſtates, gouerners, and magiſtrates of the prouinces were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded with moſt greuous puniſhmentes to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh thoſe Edictes, and to ſee them executed, and it is declared that in the behalf of the byſhop of Rome they were made onely by the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trement of the kyng.</note> without the aſſent of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates to publiſhe, and from tyme to tyme to renew moſt cruell Edictes, and ſuch as ſéeme rather to be written with bloud, then with inke, not that he ment to haue them executed with extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, but that he hoped by the terror of this vnaccuſtomed crueltie to call the peoples myndes from the ſtudie of of that religion, which he in conſcience ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compted wicked of the which his hope and meanyng he gaue no ſmale profe in that<note n="2" place="margin">That ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſicion was made and ſealed in the yeare 1550. the moneth of Septe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber.</note> expoſition of the Edictes, which he after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes ſet out, wherin it was appoincted, that the Magiſtrates ſhould by all meanes poſſible ſomewhat mitigate the extreme &amp; immoderate crueltie of the former edictes, but the good maſters of the Spaniſh Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition
<pb facs="tcp:180997:21"/>
did ſone by their craft &amp; ſubtiltie ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe that expoſition, and it came at length to that tyranie that they dyd not onelie exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the full rigour of the Edictes, but they obſerued alſo a new kynde of Inquiſition, not much vnlyke to the Inquiſition of Spayne, that thereby they might atteyne vnto the full authoritie of that office &amp; fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, which they had long before obteyned of the byſhops of Rome. Therfore in the yeare of our Lord God. 1550. when the kyng of Spayne was auctoriſed in Belgie, with great and importunate ſutes they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined an Edict as concerning their Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, whereby they dyd vſurpe &amp; take vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon them ſo much auctoritie, and power of the Citizens, and inhabitans of the whole prouince, as they thought ſufficient for the ſubuertyng of the auncient liberties, &amp; for the diſanullyng of all their accuſtomed pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uileges, but the ſenators and the eſtates of Brabant with long &amp; erneſt ſute firſt ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped this their wicked enterpriſe, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the moſt noble princes Marie of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous memorie Quene of Hungarie with great fayth, ſingular pietie, &amp; with no leſſe wiſedome ſuppeſſed it. For both when the Emperour Charles was at the counſels holden at Auguſta, ſhe went vnto him, and
<pb facs="tcp:180997:21"/>
obteyned that the crueltie of the Edictes ſhould be ſomewhat mitigated, and that the whole name &amp; purpoſe of the Inquiſition ſhould be omitted, and alſo many tymes af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhe ſtoutlie ſet her ſelfe agaynſt the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceytfull dealynges, and raſhe attemptes of the Inquiſitors and diuines, in ſo much that at the length by their letters ſent into Spayne ſhe was accuſed of hereſie before the Emperour. But ſhe alwayes bent her whole intent, and purpoſe to kepe the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Belgie in the Emperours good grace and fauour, &amp; to her power to take awaie all the enuie and hatred wherewith they were oppreſſed of their aduerſaries. With the which her moſt mercifull and wiſe dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng ſhe ſo faythfully ioyned the hartes of the ſubiectes towardes their prince, that they for her ſake thought no burden to be refuſed, in ſo much that in many thynges they dyd moſt willinglie preferre her gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious fauor and good wil before the right of their auncient liberties graunted by the lawes &amp; ſtatutes of their progenitors. For in all reſtraintes, taſkes, tributes, or leuies they ſhewed them ſelues at the firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement ſo obedient, that the princes could deſire nothyng, which was not deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered them with ful conſent of al their good
<pb facs="tcp:180997:22"/>
willes, and that with ſpede. So that almoſt for the ſpace of ten yeares, they dyd gladlie mainteyne that great, doubtfull, and moſt daungerous warre, whiche was made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the moſt mighty kings of France, &amp; they moſt willinglie beſtowed the greateſt part of the charges thereof, the which by common bookes of accompt maie be proued to ſurmount the ſomme of xl. thouſand mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions of Florence: neither dyd they geue at any tyme ſo much, as a ſmale ſuſpicion of rebellion.</p>
            <p>Although in the meane tyme neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe theſe good maiſters of the Inquiſition (whyle Charles reigned by the coulered ſhew of the foreſayd Edictes, and<note n="1" place="margin">In the yere 1555. 1. of December.</note> in the begynnyng of kyng Philips reigne by the graunt of a new Edict bearyng with it the kinges auctoritie, which they purchaſed by their ſubtell wiles, &amp; craftie perſuaſions) raiged moſt furiouſlie in the moſt part of Belgie, but eſpeciallie in Flaunders, Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonie, Arteſia, Turnete, and Inſule, &amp; in many places of Holland, robbyng ſpoiling, and moſt butcherly murderyng, the people with furious violence and extreme tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.<note n="2" place="margin">In the yere 1556. 17. Ianua.</note> From the which they abſteyned, leaſt that their deceypt, and ſubtiltye beyng de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected, this foreſayd commaundement wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted
<pb facs="tcp:180997:22"/>
out by craft, ſhould by the kynges new letters pattentes be called in agayne. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yet were they without their frendes in the Court, which beyng daylie conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant with the kyng dyd alwaies cloake and couer their crueltie and inſatiable auarice with the vayle of godlie Religion. At the length the kyng hauing ended his warre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the French men, and preparyng to take his iorney into Spayne, his ſubiectes for their ſingular obedience, and their moſt faythfull redynes in all affaires, thought they might iuſtlie hope for ſome releſſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their other burdens, but cheflie and eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allie they perſwaded them ſelues, that they ſhould haue the yoke of the Inquiſition ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from theyr ſhoulders. But the kyng was ſo farre from ſatiſfiyng their expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that he did not onelie not remit, or mitigate the crueltie vſed to them before, but alſo encreaſed, and augmented the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny, euen as though their peace &amp; other matters had bene for none other cauſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, but that they might the frelyer ſpoile poore men of their goodes, and moſt cruellie torment their conſciences,<note n="1" place="margin">This may be proued by the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters &amp; pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentes ſent to the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, in the yeare. 1559 in Auguſt.</note> For at that time eſpeciallie the Inquiſitors by their old accuſtomed deceyptes, and by the fayned ſhew of ſettyng forward religion, obteined
<pb facs="tcp:180997:23"/>
of the kyng newe letters patentes to all princes, and magiſtrates of euery Citie, by the whiche the rigoureſnes of the former Edictes was not onelie openlie confirmed, but alſo by the graunt of many thyngs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the right, and priuileges of their auncient liberties verie much encreaſed. With theſe letters the Inquiſitors beyng armed after the kynges departure, ſpoyled the poore people beyng cleane beggered be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of the remnaunt of their riches, they depriued cities and townes of their priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leges, they moſt cruelly murdered the chefe of the Citizens, hauyng firſt ſpoyled them of theyr goodes deſtroying ſome with the burden of rheynes, &amp; long empriſonment, ſome by moſt cruell tormentes, ſome by the gallowes, ſome by ſword, ſome by fire, bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying ſome quicke, and drownyng other: yee &amp; that before their cauſe was pleaded, and many tymes at midnight contrary to the accuſtomed maner of executing iuſtice.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A new cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of byſſhops.</note>And that nothyng ſhould be wantyng vnto them wherby they might bring in this their holy Inquiſition, too the vtter aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donyng, and ſubuertyng the liberties and priuileges of the whole prouinces, &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the chefe auctoritie to ſtraungers, yea to thoſe onelie whiche were Prieſtes and
<pb facs="tcp:180997:23"/>
church men, contrary to all the orders and decrées of the former princes, and contrary to the kings couenaunt confirmed by othe: &amp; whereby they might chalenge vnto them ſelues not onelie full power &amp; iuriſdiction of all matters, but alſo the ſoueraigne au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoritie ouer all mens goods, riches, wiues, children, yea ouer their lyues alſo, &amp; might captiuate and make ſubiect vnto them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues the full power of all magiſtrates, and ſet the ſame foorth to open ſale at their plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure, they begyn with a new pollicie the old web of their Inquiſition, which they had compaſſed in their mindes, but not as yet throughlie finiſhed.<note n="1" place="margin">Not long before the kynges de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uellanus &amp; Viglius, &amp; three or iiij. more onelie knowyng therof.</note> For when all the kynges nobles and counſellours were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from him, they perſwaded him that it was neceſſarie for the maintenaunce of the catholike religion to appoinct new by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, which ſhould be the Inquiſitors of fayth. The charge hereof was committed to Somnus a deuine of Louine, he goyng to Rome with great diligence brought his matter to paſſe in ſhort ſpace as he deſired, he deuided the prouinces as he was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded by Granduellanus, in the which he left not the power &amp; iuriſdictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the<note n="2" place="margin">As the byſhops of <hi>Leodia, Monaſteria, Cameracenſia,</hi> and <hi>Traiectia.</hi>
               </note> princes of the empire vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touched, ſo farre was he from let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng
<pb facs="tcp:180997:24"/>
the other byſhops, &amp; nobles to eſcape, he<note n="1" place="margin">
                  <hi>As</hi> Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuellanus Viglius, Cancella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius Niger.</note> made certein men byſhops, whiche had ſpent their whole ſtudie and trauayle all their lyfe tyme in the adminiſtration of ciuill affaires, whereof<note n="2" place="margin">Theſe may be proued by the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blike teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince, &amp; by the biſhops ſermons, &amp; by all theyr doynges.</note> ſome of them for their wit and learnyng were accompted as fooles, and others for their vnchaſt lyfe and odious crimes were famous with moſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table infamie. He aſſigned vnto Granduel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanus the Archbyſhopricke of Meclenia with the Abbacie of Afflegamenſia, the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſt &amp; moſt wealthyeſt of all Belgie, that is to ſay, he gaue him the ſoueraigne aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of all thyngs, he appoincted to Viglius the Byſhopricke of Gandauia, but to hym ſelfe he reſerued the byſhopricke of Buſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducia, and adioyned therunto many of the moſt wealthyeſt Abbayes, the which were euident ſignes and tokens of the emynent calamities &amp; publike bondage, he imparted to the reſt as their office and chardge requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,<note n="3" place="margin">This is proued by the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals decree made at Rome by the Popes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> but to euery one he obteined licence to appoint new prebendes in his cathedral Church, they which ſhould be bounde al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to ſerue and helpe the biſhop in hys Inquiſition throughout his Dioceſe, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of two of them were alwayes Inquiſitors by office, the reſt ſhould ſeaze vppon the goodes confiſcate, and ſerue for proctures
<pb facs="tcp:180997:24"/>
to accuſe the giltie, and euery magiſtrate was bounde to aide euery one of theſe with his full power and force. It was lawfull for ſtraungers to attayne to theſe byſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prickes, vnder whiche pretence the whole prouince might eaſelie, and in ſhort tyme be made ſubiect to the Spanyardes inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and maiſters of this Inquiſition.</p>
            <p>And thus this ſtraunger and vp ſtarte Granduellanus borne of a baſe degrée, and moſt obſcure parentage, with that ſlauiſhe ſecte of the Spaniſhe Inquiſitors doth<note n="1" place="margin">For by all the lawes and priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of Brabant and theyr other prouinces all eccleſiaſticall perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s were excluded from all function of iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, and iuriſdiction, and all ſtraungers are remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from takyng of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, and auctoritie, &amp; the diuiſions of byſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prickes, and Abbayes are before appoynted, &amp; the accuſtomed maner of geuyng iudgement for euer ratified, and all power is denyed to the princes to chaunge any thyng therein without the aſſent of the eſtates.</note> contrary to the whole libertie of the people, contrary to the lawes of the Citie, contrary to the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uileges of the prouince graunted &amp; confirmed by the kynges othe, contrary to all former promiſes, contrary to all rightes and cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of our progenitors, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to the makyng of lawes, the foundations of olde Abbayes, the iuriſdiction of byſhoprickes, the priuileges and immunities of townes, by force thruſt vpon the prouinces of Belgie this newe creation of byſhops. He goeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout partlie with flatteryng pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, partlie with fearefull threatnynges
<pb facs="tcp:180997:25"/>
to induce many cities &amp; magiſtrates to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie them ſelues to his cenſure and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and to ſome Cities he cauſeth by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops to be giuen them will they nill they. The reſt of the Cities a greate many in number do openly reſiſt, and thinke that the innouation of all theſe thynges ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt contrary to the lawes of all antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, &amp; to their old &amp; accuſtomed priuileges is not to be ſuffered. Likewiſe many Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bayes, but eſpeciallie in Brabant, becauſe their Abbates beyng dead none was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to ſuccede, do reſiſte, and greuouſly complaine to the reſt of the byſhops, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates of Brabant, of ſo great, and ſo mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt iniury. But when they ſaw their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynges to be in vayne, becauſe Granduel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanus did with great force withſtand them, they takyng vnto them the reſt of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, put vp a Supplication vnto theyr gouerneſſe for the abrogatyng of thys diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordered order of byſhops. She denyeth her auctoritie to reach ſo far, and referreth the matter to the kyng. Therfore by &amp; by they ſend their Embaſſadours to the kyng into Spayne, which with humble petition ſhuld require, that his maieſtie would not ſuffer their ſtate and condition to be altered, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to their old &amp; accuſtomed priuileges,
<pb facs="tcp:180997:25"/>
and to the lawes of their progenitors. But with<note n="1" place="margin">1562. 27. Februa.</note> open denyall they haue the repulſe. Not long after doe the eſtates of Brabant vrge the gouerneſſe agayne, and craue that their cauſe might be heard, and iudgement giuen with equitie,<note n="2" place="margin">1562. 5. Maij.</note> but there ſuite was all in vayne for ſhe aunſwered that it dyd nothyng belong vnto her. The Magiſtrate of Antwarpe with<note n="3" place="margin">One bill was put vp and ſubſcribed vnto, in the yeare. 1562. 23. Ianua. an other. 1562. 18. of Marche. And an other. 1562. 23. Marche.</note> many bils, &amp; diuerſe peticions dyd go about to ſtay this innouation of things. He openly refuſeth the byſhops, and beſides that<note n="4" place="margin">1562. In Iune they put vp many Sup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plications.</note> ſendeth Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours into Spayne to the kyng. They after much ado, and long ſollicityng of the matter, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined at the length<note n="5" place="margin">1562. 20. of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember, and 3. Auguſt. 1563.</note> licence to be exempted from the bondage of the new Byſhops.</p>
            <p>In the meane tyme Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uellanus neuer ceaſed by moſt ſubtill and craftye meanes, and that openlye to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieue and wynne vnto hym ſelfe the full power of gouernyng the common wealth, &amp; couertly to<note n="6" place="margin">This is knowen by the teſtimonie of the go<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerneſſe geuen in the aſſembly of the nobles.</note> remoue from all authoritie the gouerneſſe of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menia, as one not expert inough in the Belgians affaires, to<note n="7" place="margin">The dede it ſelfe pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueth it.</note> or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deine, and appointe Magiſtrates
<pb facs="tcp:180997:26"/>
in euery Citie at his pleaſure,<note n="1" place="margin">This is proued by the nobles complaints geuen to the kyng.</note> to breake of and diſturbe the great Senate, not long before appointed by the kyng, and was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the noble counſell, beyng the ſolemne aſſembly of the princes &amp; gouernors of the whole prouince (whiche<note n="2" place="margin">That was Gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>duella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus his ſtu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>die.</note> he a litle before, had with falſe perſuaſions vnto the kyng very much blemiſhed, and made ſubiect to to the counſell &amp; Senate houſe of Spayne, as it were to their guide) to cut in péeces all their decrées,<note place="margin">All Belgie can teſtifie this.</note> and to rule and appoynte all thynges alone, accordyng to his owne will and pleaſure, and by a new forme of indulgences, (as they terme them) to bring in the Spaniſhe maner of diſtributyng of benefices, and offices, both Ciuill and Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall the whiche he abuſed accordyng to his pleaſure, he challenged the whole power of indulgences to him ſelfe, leauing notwithſtanding ſome of them to Viglius, by this meanes, when offices or benefices were vacant, he ſome tymes ſtayed the gift of them for a long ſpace, and ſome tymes agayne vpon the firſt day of their vacation ſet them out to open ſayle, and ſometymes he twiſe ſolde them. The price he deuided openly with his brokers, and proctours, he accompted himſelfe the Archbiſhop of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clynia, &amp; Metropolitane not onely of Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant,
<pb facs="tcp:180997:26"/>
but alſo of the whole prouince of Bel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gie. And when he had receaued from the Pope his Cardinals batte, he diſdayned all princes in reſpect of him ſelfe. He mightely threatened thoſe Cities, whiche refuſed to ſubmitte them ſelues to the Byſhops bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, he openly did boſt and ſay, that the kyng could not mainteyne his honor, and auctoritie in Belgie, without the Spaniſhe power, &amp; foreine ayde. He ſayd it was alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether neceſſary, that the king ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſed by the biſhop of Rome from his oth, wherwith he bound himſelf by couenaunt, to mainteine the priuileges of his ſubiects, &amp; that he ſhould conuert this his lawful in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritaunce into a prouince, makyng it cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue which before was frée, as if it had bene wonne by force of armes, or conquered by battell, &amp; not enioyed by ſucceſſion of aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient patrimonie, and briefly that he ſhould make them new lawes, and inuent ſome new kynde of regiment for them like cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues taken in warre.<note n="1" place="margin">This hys ſaying was heard of ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny and ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified to the nobles, and confirmed by the kinges le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</note> He ſayd moreouer that it was neceſſary for the performaunce hereof, that 4. or 5. of the noble men ſhould leſe their heades, in whoſe auctoritie and carefull prudence, the health and ſafetie of the people, and the onely hope of their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties was thought to conſiſte. To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude
<pb facs="tcp:180997:27"/>
he openlye contemnyng the whole company of the primates and nobles, and the gouerneſſe of Permenia her ſelfe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauing him ſelfe both as King and Biſhop, by force and violence, maketh his frendes and clyentes, ſome of them Byſhops, and ſome of them Inquiſitors.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="1" place="margin">The reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the noble men.</note> When as the Princes and noble men of the prouince ſaw no end of his madnes, they thought it moſt expedient for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and for the ſtate of the whole com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon weale, wholy to withſtande his raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, perceiuing indéede manifeſtly, that if by ſome meanes or other he were not ſtayd or repreſſed, the people (though moſt paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent &amp; louing ſubiectes towardes the king) could not long be reteyned in their duetye of obedience: neither yet did they attempt then any thing by force or violence, or by any crafty and wicked enterpriſe, but they withſtoode him onely by making humble ſupplication to the King, fully certifying hys Maieſtie, that if thoſe rigorous iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes were executed ſtill with ſuch cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and that worthy Citezens were oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed wyth ſuch great tyranny, in ſo great a corruption and common pollution of all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, it was impoſſible to retayne the people any longer in theyr accuſtomed due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb facs="tcp:180997:27"/>
and faythfull obedience, but that doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe the publique ſlaughter and common deſtruction of the whole prouince, was wyth ſpéed to be looked for, vnleſſe his pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, forſéeing the miſchief dyd ſéeke ſome remedy for it with all expedition.<note n="1" place="margin">1562. the moneth of Auguſt.</note> Baron of Montignie one of the order of the gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den fléece was ſent embaſſador for the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance herof. But not long after he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned, not ſpéeding of hys purpoſe. And no maruaile why, for in Spayne all things were no leſſe gouerned by the Inquiſitors authoritie, then they were ruled in Belgye by the Cardinals will and pleaſure.</p>
            <p>But in the meane ſpace whileſt the liberty of religion was appointed in France, and publiſhed with full conſent, the Cities of Belgie, bordering vpon the Frenchmen, began openly in publique aſſemblies, and common preachings to profes the religion of the Goſpell, which for the ſpace of fortie yeares before, they kept cloſe in theyr pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate houſes. Which thing they did partly, becauſe otherwiſe they ſée they coulde not auoyd the ſlaunders and reprochfull oppro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bries, wherwith theyr priuate méetinges and ſecret conference were openly and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly defamed amongeſt the people: and partly becauſe they ſaw the daily encreaſe
<pb facs="tcp:180997:28"/>
of thoſe which profeſſed the goſpell to be ſo great, that priuate houſes could not longer contayne them: So that it was neceſſarie either to let the citezens leauing their cities voyd of men, flie to their olde enemies the Frenchmen, or els to ſatiſfy the earneſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of the people in that one poynt, which in all other thinges was moſt obedient. But by and by the extreme tyranny of the Inquiſition, and the barbarous cruelty of the puniſhments, ſomwhat repreſſed them, though (God be prayſed) it could not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether extinguiſh them. The more openly they profeſſed their fayth, the more vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly did Granduellanus ſéeke to encreaſe the number of the new biſhops, inſomuch that contrary to the will of the nobles, he attempted to depriue the citizens of Ant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werpe of the kinges beneuolence towards them, wherby they obtayned their liberty, and were made frée from that extreme bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage. He ſtyrred ſo long in this matter, that there had bene lyke to haue bene a great ſedition, if Armenter the Spayniard had not bene ſent againe to the king, by the conſent and counſell of the gouerneſſe and nobles, who plainly ſhould certefie the king that the people coulde not any longer be kept in ſubiection, &amp; that the princes them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues
<pb facs="tcp:180997:28"/>
would renounce their authority, and leaue of the ruling of the common wealth, vnleſſe it would pleaſe the kinges maieſtie to plucke in the raynes of thys vntamed Cardynall, to repreſſe and withſtande hys vnbrydeled madneſſe, to deliuer hys poore ſubiectes from the yoke of hys tyranny, to make fruſtrate his purpoſe of new altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and finally indéede to confirme and eſtabliſhe hys liberalitye and benefite be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed and graunted to the Citezens of Antwarpe.</p>
            <p>Thys pytifull complaynt ſo moued the kyng, that he ſhewed hymſelfe very angry,<note place="margin">The depar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture of Granduel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanus. 1564.</note> &amp; heauely diſpleaſed with Granduellanus, and therupon depryuing him of all hys au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritye, called hym home preſently from Belgye. By whoſe departure al the whole prouince of low Germany breathed vpon, as it were wyth a more pleaſaunt and freſh ayre, dyd ſéeme ſomewhat to reſt and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort it ſelfe, vntill ſuch tyme as thoſe good byſſhops of Spayne dyd put the kyng in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce, and cauſed hym (accordyng to theyr pleaſure) to lay the heauy yoke of the Inquiſition vpon the prouinces of Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gye agayne: and to wyll the byſhops to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the crueltye of the Edictes: and that they ſhould morouer diligently vrge againe
<pb facs="tcp:180997:29"/>
the due reuerence of the counſell of Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent. The Cardinalles miniſters (whych as hys chief frendes and ſuccourers Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uellanus had left in great authority at hys departure) do ſet this matter abroch to the vttermoſt of their power, and therwythall (accordyng to that ſtate of gouernemente which he left when he departed) they eaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wrong into their owne hands the whole rule and authoritie of the common weale. They do gouerne thrée courts of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors at theyr pleaſure: they ſpoile the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble men of all their authoritye: finally they determine and appoynt all thinges accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to theyr lewd appetite euen as though Granuellanus himſelfe were there preſent among them in authority: nothing leſſe ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to ſet vp their Inquiſition, and to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh theyr byſſhops, then they dyd before. They exerciſed all kinde of cruelty againſt thoſe that profeſſed Chriſtes Goſpell, ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to extirpate and roote them out wyth the gallowes, fire, and ſword, in ſuch ſort, that at the ſame time at Antwarpe, which is an Erldome of the holy Empyre, beſides an infinite number whom they did deſtroy ſome by day, and ſome by night, moſt cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, openly, and in the middeſt of the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ketſtead, they ſtroke one to the hart with a
<pb facs="tcp:180997:29"/>
dagger as they were a burning of hym vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a Iubbet, becauſe they ſaw that both the cruelty of the puniſhment, and the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty and godlineſſe of the man being well knowne vnto all men did ſtir vp the people to pitifull complaynt and bewayling of hys caſe. There was alſo an other man taken wyth him, whoſe pardone the noble prince Elector of Palentine (becauſe for his hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty he loued him, &amp; becauſe he was teacher &amp; maiſter of the ſchole at Hedelberge) dyd moſt earneſtly ſue for. But they wicked ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rauntes would not diſmiſſe him, before he was almoſt conſumed to death wyth a ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes taken with long impriſonment and by the filthy ſmell and ſauour therof.</p>
            <p>But to what purpoſe ſhoulde I recyte their extreame tyranny, wherwith they op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed thoſe cities in the which they might do what they liſt, with more auctoritie and leſſe daunger? ſeyng their boldnes was ſo notable, that in Cameracis a Citie, by all auncient and vndoubted right of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours, without controuerſie, obeying his lawes and ſtatutes, they were not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feard to apprehend an honeſt &amp; godly man, becauſe he preferred vppe vnto the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates a bill of ſupplication in the name of no leſſe then a M. Citizens, by whom he
<pb facs="tcp:180997:30"/>
was choſen and appointed to execute that charge, whoſe requeſt was nothyng els, but that they might fréely, &amp; with the good leaue of the Magiſtrate reteyne the confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion made at Auguſta, which they confeſſe them ſelues to folow, yet notwithſtandyng they I ſay, were bold to apprehend hym, &amp; within leſſe then 4. houres after, to behead him, though he did appeale from them to the Emperours Maieſtie, infinite is the number of ſuch thyngs, which the commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted contrary to all order of law, equitie, or right, they cauſed euery wiſe man with feare to looke for ſome open rebellion of the people, or rather the vtter ſubuerſion of the prouince, if there were not with ſpede ſome remedy taken. Therfore at the length in the name of the gouerneſſe, &amp; the nobles<note n="1" place="margin">1565.</note> Egmundanus was ſent vnto the kyng with commiſſion to declare vnto his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, that vnleſſe it would pleaſe him, to ſtay the raſh enterpriſes of certeine men, to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigate the ſeueritie of the Edictes, and vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly to aboliſhe the Inquiſition, he ſhould looke for the emynent deſtruction of the whole prouince, the kyng aunſwered hym very gently, and promiſed to pleaſure hys prouince of Belgie, in any thing, they could reaſonably requeſt ſo that in ſhorte ſpace,
<pb facs="tcp:180997:30"/>
they ſhould haue all thynges well ordered, according to their hartes deſire, he likewiſe gaue them in charge, that they ſhould take counſell together, and deuiſe ſome meanes whereby they might, without any hynde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce to the Catholicke Religion, preuent &amp; withſtand ſuch emynent daungers, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing faythfully to allow, &amp; confirme that which they ſhould lawfully deuiſe. For the ſpedie performaunce hereof, at the returne of Egmundanus to Belgie, there was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted a counſell of thrée Byſhops, thrée Diuines, thrée Canonicall Lawyers, and thrée Ciuilians, to whom the whole charge of findyng this good order was committed.</p>
            <p>Not long after beyng moued thereto by the importunate ſuyte of the Spaniſh In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitors and Byſhops, and by the letters of Gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>duellanus, but eſpecially compelled by the fearefull threatninges of the Popes Legates, thunderyng out not onely excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, but alſo eternall damnation, except he dyd by all maner of meanes, yea though it were to the vtter ſubuertion of the whole prouince of Belgie, eſtabliſh, and ſet vp the Inquiſition, and cleane roote out the leaft reliques of the new religion, he chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged his minde, &amp; vtterly refuſed the or<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der of gouernement deuiſed in Belgie, not
<pb facs="tcp:180997:31"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:180997:31"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:180997:32"/>
bycauſe it dyd not appointe moſt greuous tormentes for the Goſpellers, or bicauſe it was farre different from the rigorouſnes of the former Edictes, but bicauſe it ſemed ſomewhat more remiſſe and mercyfull in certeine pointes,<note n="1" place="margin">The kings decree, by the which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tumultes of Belgye began. 1565. December.</note> laſtly by his letters he ſtreightly commaundeth that the Inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhould be eſtabliſhed and ſet vp, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughout all Belgie, and that to the Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitors of euery prouince, and the chief coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellours thereof, ſhould adioyne them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, and ayde, and helpe them, with their counſell and force to the vttermoſt of their power, that all old Edictes ſhould be execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in euery pointe, the Byſhops ſhould be admitted and inſtalled in euery Citie, the decrées of the councell of Trident ſhould be publiſhed euery where. And briefly that nothyng ſhould be omitted whiche ſerueth to the rootyng out of thoſe, whiche profeſſe the Goſpell. Moreouer he very much bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the Iudges and Magiſtrates of euery prouince that they did not with more ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie execute the popes edicts &amp; his decrées, attributing the cauſe of all hereſies to their diſſolute negligence and fooliſh pitie.</p>
            <p>When theſe letters were receiued con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to all mens expectation, &amp; were ſent to the Magiſtrates of euery prouince, and
<pb facs="tcp:180997:32"/>
that the kings laſt wil was openly knowen and publiſhed, great heauynes, great trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of mynde, finally great feare and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour came vpon them all. The eſtates of Brabantie put a bill to the gouerneſſe, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claryng that it neither could, nor ought to be brought to paſſe in that wiſe, in their prouince, yet they could get no certein aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, but one very darke &amp; doubtfull, and that a great while after, the ſame was done of the Flaundrians, the Namurcenſians, the Geldrians, and of the other prouinces next adioynyng, yea and that the Church men and Abbottes, to be brief there was ſo great amaſe &amp; terrour amongeſt all men, that they all of what degrée or eſtate ſo euer they were of, feared their owne ſafetie: they ſée all their hope &amp; confidence, whiche they were wont to put in their innocencie and honeſt lyfe, cleane taken away. They ſée it impoſſible for any man to eſcape the raſh attemptes, the troubleſome cauils, &amp; malicious ſclaunders of the wicked. For by this meanes, any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> might conuey into euery good mans houſe, chamber, or cheſts, ſome of the forbydden bookes, of the which there was an innumerable company. And ſo cauſe them to be ſuſpected, and accuſed of hereſie: they dyd ſée alſo that no man
<pb facs="tcp:180997:33"/>
could eſcape or a voyde the tyranny of the Edictes, bicauſe by them not onely they which were found gilty, but all their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours frendes kinſmen, &amp; acquaintaunce were lykewiſe puniſhed by moſt horrible death, vnleſſe they of them ſelues would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray their moſt deare and familiar frendes. To conclude they did lykewiſe ſée, that if they ſhould ceaſe &amp; leaue of from their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, all hope of forgeuenes to be taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and that for their great benefites, and good will, they ſhould be rewarded not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with great &amp; infamous ignominie with bondage and troubles of conſcience, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo with moſt extreme and cruell death. The whiche truly the barbarous crueltie of the Spaniſhe Inquiſition could neuer abyde for they thus thought, and perſwaded them ſelues, that if they, when for want of fauor &amp; auctoritie they could ſcarce execute theyr office of Inquiſition, dyd not omitte any kynde of crueltie, would now become in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable frée men ſeyng as that they haue for their defence and ſafegard the manifeſt and vnmoueable will of the kyng, the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoritie of the publike Edites, the helpe, &amp; induſtrie of counſellers a great increaſe of new biſhops, the glorious title of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Trident, the power of Magiſtrates,
<pb facs="tcp:180997:33"/>
the violence, and force of Sergeauntes and ſouldiers redy to defend them in the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng of their tyranny, and therfore euery man was in moſt deſperate feare. Neither did any perſwade him ſelfe (except he were of the number of thoſe Catchepoles and théeues, to auoyde or put from his goodes and ſubſtaunce, his wife and children, yea from his owne head, ſo great calamitie. If there were any, who for the great fauour they were in, or for their great power and auctoritie, might in this point haue perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them ſelues ſecuritie, as there were ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry few, yet bicauſe they dyd playnly foreſée, that this tyranny continued would cauſe ſome tumultes or open rebellion, they fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red no leſſe, then the reſt dyd, the ſpoyle of their goodes and poſſeſſions, with loſſe of their lyues. In this great aſtoniſhment of all men, &amp; heauines of the whole prouince? Many of the chiefeſt and wealthyeſt mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chauntes, who perſwaded them ſelues that their matter was in handlyng, and that the wicked dyd ſéeke for their throtes, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, by their throtes their golden coffers, bagges and iewels, preparyng to flye, It came to paſſe that many of the nobilitie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng moued with the publike daunger, and their owne perill, both bicauſe the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall
<pb facs="tcp:180997:34"/>
complaintes, and murmurynges of the people were dayly brought vnto them, and bicauſe their houſes, and gorgeous pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laces, beyng in the fieldes, were ſubiect to the praye and ſpoyle of euery ſeditious tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multe, thought it neceſſary with one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to goe vnto the gouerneſſe, and to make playne and open vnto her, the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable deſtruction and calamities which are incident and lyke to enſue to the kyng hym ſelf, to his louyng ſubiectes, to his Cities, and to his whole prouince, if this his Edict ſhould haue his full force and power, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when they had made a league or agrée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment amongeſt them ſelues as concerning this matter, and had promiſed that euery one of them, (kepyng their fayth and loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to their kyng vnuiolated, ſhould ſéeke to the vttermoſt of their power the ſubuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and ouerthrowe of this Inquiſition, and to cauſe the ſeueritie of the Edictes to be mitigated,<note place="margin">1566. A co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming together of the nobles. A ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> came together at Bruxels the v. of Aprill very neare thrée hundreth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, &amp; Brederodes beyng their captaine. They put vp vnto the gouerneſſe, a bill of ſupplication in the which they required no libertie for them ſelues, or the people, no alteration of Religion, neither did they by their auctoritie take vpon them to preſcribe
<pb facs="tcp:180997:34"/>
any thyng to the kinges Maieſtie, but brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rehearſing the daungerous perils &amp; mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable calamities, which dyd then hang ouer their heades, they moſt humbly deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that the office of the Inquiſitors, ſo manifeſtly agaynſt the kynges honour, and the ſafety of the countrey might be taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way &amp; abrogated. And that it would pleaſe the kyng and his counſell to deuiſe ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Edict for the mainteynaunce of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, to the which al the inhabiters of Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, of what ſtate or condition ſo euer they were of, ſhould be bound to obey, and that the execution of the Edictes might be ſo long ſtayed, til ſuch time as that the nobles and eſtates of the countrey, after the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of their auncetours, &amp; accordyng to the cuſtome of all well ruled co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealthes, might come together to the eſtabliſhyng of them by the kynges auctoritie. Moreouer they proteſted that if by the contempt and neglectyng of this theyr requeſt, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon weale hereafter ſhould fall into any daunger, they them ſelues were by any right, not to be accuſed for it, ſeyng they had ſatiſfied their duety in forwarnyng the ſame, this humble ſute of the nobilitie was accompted iuſt and godly, not onely, of the reſt of nobles, but alſo of the gouerneſſe
<pb facs="tcp:180997:35"/>
her ſelfe, of all the Senate, &amp; of the whole concourſe of people, ſo that by their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon conſent and open ſuffragies the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerneſſe agréed, and promiſed to the vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of her power to get their requeſt ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and that ſhe would ſend her Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours to the kyng, who ſhould declare the whole matter vnto him, and bring to paſſe, (if it were poſſible) that their requeſt ſhould be graunted, and there withall they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed the Baron of Montygay, and Mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ques Bergye to performe that legaſie, and in the meane tyme, ſhe promiſed, that their ſhould be a vacation and reſpite from the execution of the cruell Edictes, and from the blouddy butchery of the Inquiſition, which ſhe would faythfully performe, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundyng the ſame by her auctoritie, ſet forth by writyng. This chaunged all theyr ſorow and heauy chere into an inſpeakea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble gladnes, &amp; made them all to hope well, In ſo much that not onely they which had determined to flye before, dyd not onely chaunge their mindes, but they which were gone all redy, tooke counſell how to come home agayne.</p>
            <p>Theſe matters ſore troubled the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals ſubſtitutes, the maiſters of the Spay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh inquiſition, and the whole company of
<pb facs="tcp:180997:35"/>
the byſhops, and catchpoles, which had in their mindes already deuoured and ſwalo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed vp the goodes and bloud of the nobleſt and richeſt men in the countrey. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they tryed all manner of wayes, how they might recouer ſo rich a ſpoyle, and ſo fat a pray, which was by thys meanes by force pluckt out from betwéene their grée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy iawes, they accuſed with moſt ſlaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous cauilles, the force of the noble men, they go about to proue that it ſhould be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for a manifeſt ſigne of a rebellion to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde, they affirme that the noble men ſéeke onely to rayſe a tumult, that thereby they might ruſhe in by force vppon other mens goodes, that they might pay theyr deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes with other mens riches, ſo craftely at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned, yea that they did ſéeke the death of all prieſtes and ſacrificers, and the ſubuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of churches, and the ouerthrow of ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: They fayned much more, the whych they ſo cunningly perſwaded the Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that ſhe leauing Bruxill the moſt aun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cient demeane and manſion of the Duke of Brabant, neuer determined to flye to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny defected city, the which truely ſhe would haue done, if being perſwaded by the noble men which they well knew the ſtate of the countrey, ſhe had not comforted her ſelfe, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:180997:36"/>
pluckt vp her courage. But when they ſée theyr manifold and ſhamefull ſlaunders di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſproued by the déed it ſelfe,<note place="margin">Slaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the aduerſaries</note> and by the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt behauiour of the noble men to take no place, they merueylouſly dyd cry out, and inuey before the Gouerneſſe agaynſt the ſolemne and great aſſembly of the nobles, againſt theyr league and ſociety which they had made, and when they did ſée that al this could litle preuayle agaynſt them, they beat moſt vpon thys one poynt, and they made thys the chiefe cauſe of theyr accuſation, that they dyd manifeſtly ſhew them ſelues ſeditious rebels, when they required a frée &amp; lawfull aſſembly of noble men, or graund parlament to be ſommoned, affirming that nothing doth more diminiſh the power and authoritie of a prince, then the ſolemne me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng of the eſtates, wherewith moſt migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty kinges and princes haue bene compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to yelde to theyr order. And truely all men do know, that Granuellanus and Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glius were wont oftentimes to ſay that the king aboue all thynges had néede to take héed, leaſt the eſtates of the prouince be ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſed to make aſſemblies and general me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinges according to the accuſtomed maner of their Auncytors, the which kinde of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment Charles the fifte dyd dyligently
<pb facs="tcp:180997:36"/>
obſerue, contrary to the cuſtome of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer princes and dukes, whereby he deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined all thinges according to hys will and pleaſure: and therfore he cleane put down the generall méetinges and lawfull aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies of all the eſtates holden at their grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d counſels, and appoynted all thynges to be done and determined after hys and theyr arbitriment whome he would vouchſafe to take vnto hym. They ſayd the king ſhould take the ſame order, if he would haue hys dignity maytayned ſafely wythout appay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and that he ſhoulde hate nothing ſo much as the very mention of thoſe frée aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblyes. But when they perceyued them ſelues to profite nothing by thys meanes, becauſe all of them wyth one voyce did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to haue a parliament, and euery man (vnleſſe he were wythout ſence or reaſon) did eaſely perceaue, the royall dignity could be mayntayned by nothyng ſo well, as by theſe general and frée aſſemblies: and they all knew that their care was for themſelues and for theyr riches, and not for the defence of the kinges honor: for at the time of the parliament, they ſhould render vp theyr ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comptes of the common treaſurye, what they had receyued and ſpent ſince the time they haue bene in theyr office: and then
<pb facs="tcp:180997:37"/>
were the actions of extortions and of the robberies of the common treaſurye to be pleaded: they thought it therefore beſt co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertly by guile and crafty meanes to worke ſome ſleight, whereby they might vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the godly endeuour of the nobles and chief citizens whatſoeuer, and cleare kéepe backe the appoyntment of theſe ſolemne counſels, therfore ſubtelly they perſwaded the Gouerneſſe that ſhe ſhoulde call the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates of euery prouince ſeuerally, and that ſhe ſhould ſuffer none to be of the counſell, but ſuch as ſhe ſhould chuſe and call ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto. And therfore as they gaue her coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell,<note place="margin">In the yere 1566. in the moneth of May.</note> ſhe cauſed moſt haſty and troubleſome aſſemblies to be made of euery prouince ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerally by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues: vnto the whych were ſommoned to appeare onely they whych were choſen: but they whom to haue bene there it had bene moſt requiſite, and they which by auncient right, and of a long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance were wont to be preſent, were now cleane omitted. Many were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded openly to depart, and many to kéepe ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence: the time of deliberating the matter, and taking counſell with theyr frends, and wyth the reſt of the eſtates of the prouince and gouernors of the people (as the moſt auncient and certayne cuſtome of ſuch aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblyes
<pb facs="tcp:180997:37"/>
hath euer before grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted, is now from all of them indifferently taken away. Moreouer the chiefeſt prouinces of all Bel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gie, whoſe cauſe eſpecially was then in handlyng, as <hi>Brabantia, Hollandia, Phri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia, Geldria, Zelandia,</hi> and the countreys of <hi>Lymburgye,</hi> beyng made vnlawfull for any of them to come thether, and thus the maner of mitigatyng theſe Edictes was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to a very ſmall company. Wherof it is manifeſt that the moſt part were ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and hyred for that purpoſe, whoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination in outward ſhew ſemed to be much ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tler, but in the right meanyng and true vnderſtandyng of it was crueller a great deale then the former Edictes, In this one pointe, it ſéemed to be more mercy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full, bicauſe in ſtede of burnyng of them, it appointed them to be truſt vp vpon a gib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet or gallowes, tormented with a racke &amp; chaynes. And for the Inquiſition ſubſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a viſitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, it did not confiſcat the goodes of theſe whiche were fled, but it ſo fetcht the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſo circumuented them, that a very foole might eaſely perceiue, they ſought nothing els, but a more priuy entraunce to their old preſcriptions and accuſtomed crueltie, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cially ſeyng the gouerneſſe did manifeſtly write vnto the gouernours, and chief Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices
<pb facs="tcp:180997:38"/>
of euery prouince, that as concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng the kynges Edictes for religion they ſhould well vnderſtand, that they ought nothyng to remitte or mitigate the ſeueri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of them, no not although ſhe her ſelfe ſhould commaunde to the contrary. And ſeyng the fury and madnes of the Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitors did no leſſe outragiouſlye robbe and ſpoyle, then they were wont to doe, and that without puniſhment or prohibition, &amp; ſeyng as that the Monkes and preachyng Friers dyd not onely with moſt bytyng tauntes and ſpitefull reproches defame the chief and noble eſtates,<note place="margin">This was ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly heard in the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches at Antwerpe and in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other places.</note> anymatyng &amp; har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſing the rude people agaynſt thoſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which put vp the bill of ſupplication &amp; alſo out of their pulpites did by name open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accuſe them of diſobedience, diſloyaltie, and ſeditious treaſon, and threaten them that the kyng would vtterly deſtroy them, and put them to death. And to conclude ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing euery man dyd by moſt euident tokens perceiue, and ſeyng they had it proued by many mens letters, and talke, that they ſought nothyng els, but by ſome meanes to delude and deceiue the people, that from them gettyng ayde, they might execute their tyranny not onely vppon the commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naltie, but euen alſo vppon the chiefeſt of
<pb facs="tcp:180997:38"/>
the Princes whoſoeuer, as if they were their deadly enemies. At the le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandyng when they had determined what ſhould be done, they offer vp to the eſtates of Brabant, the maner of their gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but in all the haſt, not lookyng for any aunſwere, they cauſed it to be publiſhed. But whileſt thoſe thynges were a doyng, the profeſſors of the Goſpell, which had he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto kept them ſelues in their priuate houſes, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hope, that at length their muſe beyng heard, and the ſlaunderous cauilles, wherewith they were defamed, fully aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, they ſhould haue libertie for their religion, which they were ready to defend, with the worde of God, in as ample ſorte graunted them, as it was to the frenchmen by theyr king and the whole aſſent of hys noble eſtates, perceyuing theyr hope and expectation fruſtrate, and themſelues to be dayly more and more ſlaundred, and that there was no more hope left, eyther in the kinges clemency, or in the expectation for the parlament, of hauing their cauſe heard, much leſſe of equall iudgement. And yet notwithſtanding all of them euery where dyd not ceaſe to call for the preaching of the goſpell, inſomuch that the multitude could not be contayned in any priuate houſes.
<pb facs="tcp:180997:39"/>
Many of them began in the vttermoſt bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Flaunders, where the tyranny of the Inquiſition had moſt extreamly perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted them, and by and by in Brabant, in Holland, and alſo the reſt of the prouinces, to come together into the fields to the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of Gods word, and openly to ſet forth theyr doctrine, that at the length they might cleare themſelues from the ſlaunderous ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils of theyr owne aduerſaries, being their Iudges, and that all men might know who they were, what kinde of men they were, what number was of them, and of what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimation or worſhip they were of, firſt they came to all aſſemblies without weapons.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The aduer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſaries pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes to op<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>preſſe the Goſpellers.</note>But when theyr aduerſaries began ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to threaten vnto them moſt extreme cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty, many of them got theyr wepons, ſome a ſword, ſome a ſpeare, ſome a club, as men vſe them, when they prepare to take ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, but a very few brought dagges: but within a whyle after theyr number began to encreaſe to many thouſandes of people. When the Cardinalles Vicegerentes per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued they could not be oppreſſed without open violence, becauſe by reaſon of theyr great number, of theyr fauour and power, of the equitie of theyr cauſe, of the honeſty of theyr lyfe, of the integritie of theyr acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb facs="tcp:180997:39"/>
they were becom maruelouſly ſtrong. But eſpecialy when they ſaw the moſt part of the nobilitie openly fauoryng theyr cauſe (whoſe deſire of publike peace which they of late had ſhewed foorth in theyr bill of ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, and all theyr actions were ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered very much wyth ſundry ſlaunderous cauils) they flye vnto theyr crafts &amp; guiles. They by ſundry and many wayes deceiued the nobilitie, which came together in a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne aſſembly at Sainttrudo to take coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell for the ſauegard of themſelues, and for the aunſwering of the moſt reprochfull ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils, and the auoyding of theyr violent raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Firſt, they go about to perſwade them to become the open enemies of the publike preaching, and to diſpatch them by force of armes. But perceiuing themſelues to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour therin in vayne, becauſe many of the nobles dyd reſiſt them, which were profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of that religion, they compaſſed theyr matter about an other way, fayning them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to require theyr helpe for to pacifie the tumults of the people. Therefore pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding many commaundementes, they obtayned that Embaſſitors ſhould be ſent from among them vnto the Gouerneſſe of Permence, the which ſhould determine vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon all matters according to equitie and
<pb facs="tcp:180997:40"/>
right, as beſt ſhould be thought for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> profite of the common wealth: The Embaſſadors mening ſimply,<note place="margin">This com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, or determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion began firſt at Bruxels the 24. 25. and 26. of Auguſt. an. 1566.</note> went w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> them vnto Bruxell. The gouerneſſe deſireth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the tumultes of the people with all theyr power, and to obey the king and his magiſtrates with all obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, not once minding to take vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, but leauing all fond &amp; ſiniſter ſuſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, &amp; to perſwade themſelues that the king would very well allow of their doings, &amp; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt it a full ſatiſfaction of their duties: ſhe likewiſe graunteth at theyr requeſt, that it ſhalbe lawfull for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to kéepe theyr publike ſermons in their accuſtomed places as they haue done heretofore. It was ſolemply alſo decréed on both parties, that by the auctority of the magiſtrates there ſhould be appointed common places in euery citie &amp; town, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they might make their ſermons, and fréely without all feare exerciſe their preachings, &amp; that the profeſſing of religion ſhould be hurt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full to none, ſo that he obſerued his duty in all other matters without inuading of chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, or mouing any tumults herafter: they promiſed faythfully on both parties, but the Cardinals men bound themſelues by oth, &amp; by theyr holy deuotion, to be faithfull in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming their promiſe. The gouerneſſe for her part, to make it more ſure calleth a coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſell of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nobles, who likewiſe promiſed their
<pb facs="tcp:180997:40"/>
fidelity in performing the ſame &amp; ſhe geueth forth letters patents auctoriſed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the kings broad ſeale. Not lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g after ſhe ſendyng theſe letters to the gouernours and<note n="1" place="margin">
                  <p>The proue hereof ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peareth both by the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> letters pate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, &amp; by the Edicte of the Magiſtrates firſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed, &amp; after publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in Print.</p>
                  <p>The Edictes for cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing from raylyng was proclaymed at Ant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werpe, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt of Auguſt. an. 1566. at Bruxelles. 24. of Aug. y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Earle of Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſfeld beyng preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Free libertie of prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyng came from the gouerneſſe. 25. of Aug.</p>
               </note> Magiſtrates of euery prouince ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueth in commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement that this agréement ſhould bee promulga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and that the whole common wealth ſhould be gouerned accor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyng to the come<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes therof, &amp; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward by<note n="2" place="margin">An other publicke Edict concernyng ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng &amp; reuilyng on both partes to ceaſe was pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>claimed at Antwerpe 3. Septemb. at Bruxels, 6. Septe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>b. And ſo after<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ward in other Cities.</note> publicke Edicts ſhe forbiddeth that any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uile or ſpeake euil of others, for religion ſake, ſeyng ſhe dyd pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce that all men of both reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions were in the kyngs ſafe go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement and good protection.</p>
            <p>It happened in the meane tyme, whiles thoſe thynges were a doyng at Bruxels, it firſt in the Weaſt partes of<note n="3" place="margin">The 11. 12. 13. of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt. 1566.</note> Fraunders, and afterwardes in many other<note n="4" place="margin">At Antwerpe. 20. Auguſt. At Brede, at Buſcodice. 22. 23. In Holland and Zeland. 25. 26. &amp;c.</note> Cities almoſt at the ſame tyme Images, pictures, &amp; aulters were ouerthrowen in the Churches, whether by craft of the aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes, which euen now dyd ſéeke all occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to accuſe the people, that hauyng ſome fayre ſhew, they might
<pb facs="tcp:180997:41"/>
gather an army, or by the fonde zeale of ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny, which thought they could not earneſtly repent them of their ſinnes, vnles they had ouerthrowen the inſtrumentes of idolatry, it is as yet vncerteine. But this is moſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paraunt that in many<note n="1" place="margin">As in Ant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werpe, is Brede, in Brabant, &amp; in many pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces of Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</note> Cities the ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Prieſtes them ſelues began firſt to ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry out of their Churches, their moſt preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous reliques and veſſels, &amp; that then boyes, &amp; raſcall people followyng them, dyd ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwe the reſt, and in many Cities. It is knowen alſo that the byſhops them ſelues, and they which were the greateſt aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes of the Goſpel, dyd by publike<note n="2" place="margin">At Gaunt, in Flaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders: At Hago, in Holla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. At Lire in Brabant: Alſo at Meklyne this was done moſt certeinely by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the magi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtrates. 5. 25. 28. of Aug. and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dayes folowyng.</note> autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie ouerthrow the Images, pictures, and the reſt of the ceremonyes, and that by their authoritie and example, many good &amp; godly Citizens dyd the ſame likewiſe, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing this their doyng, to be commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the authoritie of the Magiſtrate.</p>
            <p>But how ſoeuer it came to paſſe, the Cardinals officers and Inquiſitors tooke a very fitte occaſion hereby to execute their purpoſe, for by and by they in all haſt ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theryng ſouldiours together, apprehended many of thoſe, whiche ouerthrew the Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and caſt them into priſon, and hanged them, neither could they by any queſtions, or kinde of tormentes, enforce them to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:180997:41"/>
(the which thyng they moſt gréedely deſired) that any of the Miniſters of the Churches, or any of the confederate prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which were at the foreſayd aſſembly, or any of the profeſſors of the Goſpel, were authors of this enterpriſe. But rather they did all with one voyce confeſſe that (as it was moſt manifeſt by their preachynges and endeuours, wherewith they did diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that enterpriſe) it was done contrary to all their willes, and not without their great grief and ſorow. Therfore the gouer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe dyd not<note n="1" place="margin">As appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth by the forme of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> latter E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictes made &amp; ſet forth touchyng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtay of reui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyng words &amp; of Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches graun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the former pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uention be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene the gouernes &amp; the people.</note> ceaſſe to ſée the former con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract of gouernyng the common wealth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted, in ſo much that ſhe gaue by publike auctoritie vnto many of the nobles and of the confederate princes charge ouer cities, in the whiche they ſhould ſet all thynges in order, accordyng to the due preſcript of the former decrée, that they ſhould aſſigne pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces out for the buildyng of Churches, and for the peoples aſſembly to heare Sermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and that they ſhould with open proteſtation will all men to be ſecure and voyde from all feare and daunger, and certeinly to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade them ſelues, that the gariſons of ſoul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>diours ſhould nothyng endammage them. With the whiche thyng, all the people be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan excedyngly to reioyce, and to lay a part
<pb facs="tcp:180997:42"/>
all feare, as though out of a moſt boyſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous tempeſte they were already arriued in a moſt quiet hauen, &amp; ſtayeng them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues vpon the publike promiſe thus made &amp; taken and confirmed by writyng. They be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to builde their Churches, and fréely &amp; quietly to ſet forth their religion. But yet notwithſtandyng the furious madnes of their aduerſaries was not pacified, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they had already puniſhed the ouer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>throwers of their Images with greuous puniſhementes, and did ſée the innocencie of theſe Churches moſt manifeſtly witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by their open confeſſions. But rather moſt proudly auauntyng them ſelues, as though they had gotten a iuſt occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the rebelles, and that they ſhould no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng feare hereafter the nobilitie, the whiche did manifeſtly ſhew them ſelues to be heauely diſpleaſed with the inſolency of of the Imagebreakers, they began by litle and litle but openly to encreaſe the nomber of their garriſons, and to ſet them in their Cities, with this pretence onely to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the inſolencie of the Imagebreakers, and thus they armed them ſelues, with all thynges neceſſary, vntill ſuch tyme, that they had brought their matters to as good effect, as they deſired perceiuyng the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb facs="tcp:180997:42"/>
quietly to reſt them ſelues vppon the faythful promiſe of the nobilitie and gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſet forth in the kinges name vnder hys ſeale and letters patentes, and that the noble men alſo were quiet, not once myſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubting that they ſhould haue bene ſo wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly and vnfaythfully deceaued, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan openly to ſhew foorth what theyr mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning was: for in ſuch places where as they might be moſt bolde, and in the which the magiſtrate was appliable vnto their deſire, firſt with new commaundementes, obſcure and doubtfull edictes, and with ſcoffing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation, they began to diſanull the auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tority of the publiſhed commaundement as concerning the late contract, and in many places to delay from day to day, the ſealing of the writings of the publike promiſe, and with ſundry cauils to deceaue the miſerable citizens, and in many places to put thoſe magiſtrats whoſe dealing they knew wold be alwayes with iuſtice, out of their offices, and contrary to the orders of the cities, in their roomes to ſubſtitute moſt wicked men prompt and redy to all kinde of impietie: and then at the length (as though all hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draunces had bene taken away) they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan with great inſolency by force of armes to diſturbe the companies aſſembled at ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons
<pb facs="tcp:180997:43"/>
tauntingly to reuile the miniſters and citizens, to worne them with wepons, and laſtly, with open tyranny to oppreſſe them, impriſoning many, hanging many, banyſhing many, and appointing new kind of othes, wherby men ſhould binde them to the popiſh religion, contrary to the former decrée, couenaunted and eſtabliſhed before, and to accompt thoſe which denied to obey, for enemies and traytors to the kinges ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie. Morouer they did rebaptize infantes which were baptized before: they ſpoyled all the profeſſors of the Goſpell, of theyr weapons and armour: they armed and ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp the reſt of the comminaltie agaynſt them, as agaynſt the enemies of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth. Neyther onely did the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficing prieſtes or preachers out of their pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits, as it were with an open outcry ſtir vp the people to take armour agaynſt them, but alſo in many places the Magiſtrates themſelues, which were appoynted by the Cardinals officers and Inquiſitors, ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding allarum, gaue open licence vnto the ſedition and tumultes of the people againſt the miſerable Goſpellers, the which were then lately called Gweſians, that is to ſay, Beggers and raſcals. And hereupon began the moſt dolefull and late calamitie of the
<pb facs="tcp:180997:43"/>
noble prouince. For euen then firſt of all was that famous citie of the Valentians beſéeged in enemies wiſe of hys owne fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar frendes and citizens, becauſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth they refuſed vppon the ſodaine to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue within theyr walles the cruell ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in that number that was commaunded them, that is to ſay, foure bandes of horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and fiue enſignes of footmen, but tooke vnto them a day to deliberate, in alleaging many cauſes that it would not be commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious vnto them to receaue them, ſéeing they had as yet before theyr eyes amongs theyr neighbours a moſt cruell and doleful preſident of the ſouldiers raſhnes, for not long before in the countrey and towne of Sancto Amandus nexte adioyning vnto them, the very ſame (which were thruſt in contrary to theyr lawes and priuiledges, &amp; contrary to the fidelitie of the promiſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore geuen) violently robbed and ſpoyled the poore miſerable people that profeſſed the Goſpell, of all they had, in ſo much that from the very yong infantes they pulled theyr hoſe from theyr legges, they deflou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by courſe one after an other (after the moſt horrible example of the Beniauntes) the chaſte matrones and virgines, and at length in moſt cruell wiſe, ſet them to open
<pb facs="tcp:180997:44"/>
ſale, at the ſounde of the drome, they put to death many, burnyng them by litle and litle with ſmall flames, and with theyr ſwordes opened the wombes of matrones great with childe. The remembraunce of which horrible thynges, iuſtly terrifieng the <hi>Valentenentians,</hi> they humbly deſired that they ſhould not be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelled to receaue within their walles and houſes ſuch kynde of ſouldiers, vnto whoſe auarice, luſt, and crueltie, they perceiued them ſelues, their lyues, wiues, children, and conſciences, ſhould be at le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth in moſt ſeruile bondage, ſeyng that for foure yeares ſpace before, they had payed of their own proper coſtes and charges, vnto the garriſons of ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, their wages, vpon this condition, that they ſhould neuer hereafter bee vexed or burdened any more with ſouldiours. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yet dyd they ſo manifeſtly refuſe it, but that they dyd openly in moſt humble wiſe ſignifie vnto the gouerneſſe, and to the reſt of the primates, &amp; rulers of the prouince, that they were ready to receaue the ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours of what nomber ſoeuer, if they had a capitaine appointed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for that they ſhuld not hinder the libertie of Religion, whiche they had graunted &amp; confirmed vnto them, not long before, by the Edict of the gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:180997:44"/>
by the authoritie of the kynges let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters patentes, by the nobilities conſtant confirmation, and with aſſent of all the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates. But they nothyng at all preuay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, by this their modeſtie and equitie of their cauſe, but forthwith they were open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proclaimed as traytors and rebelles, the Citie was beſieged, vntill that at the le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth when they (beyng perſuaded therto by the letters of the gouerneſſe promiſing all kind of clemency) had yelded them ſelues vnto the fidelitie of the <hi>Norcarmyans,</hi> whiche dyd beſiege them, many were ſtroken with the ſword, many were hanged, many were burned, and an infinite number of them by the inſolencie of the ſouldiers ſhot through with dagges, neither was there any thyng pretermitted agaynſt them, the whiche the furious rage of the ſouldiours vſe to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute in the ſackyng and ſubuertyng of Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. Many beyng terrified with theſe hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible examples of crueltie, and perceiuyng them ſelues ſo deceiued to be defended fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the furie and raſhnes of the ſouldiours, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the publike promiſe, agréements co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenauntes or othes, nor by the kynges ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie Edictes or patentes, and perceauyng their aduerſaries to attempt and put in pra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctiſe all kynde of hoſtilitie agaynſt them,
<pb facs="tcp:180997:45"/>
with great power and warlyke force, and that all the hope of remedy or helpe was cleane taken away, for their aduerſaries dyd now accompt them not onely as here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes, but alſo as ſeditious rebelles, as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbers of the common of the quiet, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwers of churches and traytours to the kinges maieſtie, and although they by moſt manifeſt proues, and by the open confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of thoſe, which were giltie, had proued their innocencie, &amp; had of their own accord offered them ſelues to be tryed by the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of equall iudges, they did vnderſtand neuertheleſſe that they were accuſed vnto the king of theſe moſt horrible crimes, they thought it beſt therfore to betake them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues to prayer, to vowes, to teares and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications, hopyng by their humble ſuyte &amp; iuſt purgation to pacifie the anger of the kyng, vehemently builded agaynſt them, by the falſe cauils of their aduerſaries. They therfore put vp a bill of ſupplication wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they might requeſt the kynges clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie teſtifieng their owne innocencie and the ſclaunderous accuſations, of their aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and eſpecially cleare them ſelues of the deſtroying of the Churches, prouyng them ſelues to be in no faulte, and that no ſuſpition of rebellion ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iuſtly be gathered
<pb facs="tcp:180997:45"/>
vpon them, moſt humbly proteſtyng alſo their fidelitie, obedience, &amp; due reuerence, to be alwayes ready vnto the kynges maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, in what things ſoeuer? thus much one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly crauyng at the kynges handes that they may haue frée libertie grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted them, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe their religion, which they make ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect onely to the triall of the word of God, &amp; that they may not haue their conſciences greued, or burdened with any kynde of au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, for the whiche benefite in token of their thankefulnes, and for due profe of their faithful obedience to his maieſtie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides their ordinary giftes, their accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med tributes, and all their other burdens, they promiſe to pay vnto the kings Exchec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker iij. hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dreth thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Florences within a certeine time, &amp; that they wil diſturbe or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy no churches, but they will put in good ſureties for the ſame, that they will dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and carefully ſhew forth their obedience, fidelitie, and due reuerence in all poyntes.</p>
            <p>All the Cities well neare doe geue vp to their Magiſtrates a bill of ſupplicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Nouember. 1566.</note> moſt humbly deſiryng to ſhew foorth their dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and fidelitie towardes their poore &amp; miſerable Citizens in the furtheryng ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.<note place="margin">December.</note> They do moreouer earneſtly requeſt the ſame thyng of the gouerneſſe &amp; nobles,
<pb facs="tcp:180997:46"/>
and bicauſe they would trye all maner of meanes, whereby they might make mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt to all the world their true fidelitie, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes their kyng, they ſent alſo their let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and Embaſſadors to many of the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Germanie, whom they iudged alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether not to abhorre from their religion, moſt earneſtly deſiryng them, that they would vouchſafe to entreate the kyng to be mercyfull to their innocencie, &amp; if there were any place frée from the falſe accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of their aduerſaries, and left vnto the kynges maieſtie for equitie and mercy, that they would with their humble ſuyte deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer them from their heauy calamitie, han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyng ouer their heades. But when they perceiued that all theſe thynges dyd litle preuaile, and that their aduerſaries were more kyndled and cruell agaynſt them, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretyng all thynges into the worſt part, as though by the great ſomme of money offred, they had boſtyngly auaunted their riches and power, and that they went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to threaten the kynges maieſtie, myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng to abuſe the princes of Germany, for to diſturbe and withſtand his will and plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure, and ſeyng alſo no place to be left for their purgation or humble ſupplication be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their Magiſtrates, that their eares,
<pb facs="tcp:180997:46"/>
their eyes, thoughtes, and cogitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s were made ſubiect to the accuſations of theyr ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries, they did at the length wyth moſt dolefull lamentation complayne vnto Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derodius &amp; other of the nobles (the which by the commaundement of the Gouerneſſe had promiſed theyr fayth and fidelity to the perfourmance of the former contract) that they were ſo iniuſtly and vnfaithfully dealt withal, contrary to theyr publicke promiſe, to theyr couenaunts graunted and perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by oth, and they entreat them to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme that which they ſo faythfully promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the commaundement of the Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and alſo the nobles. Brederodius in the name of the other princes,<note place="margin">Februar. 8. 1567.</note> ſending hys letters to the gouerneſſe deſireth licence to ſpeake with her: but hauing the repulſe, he ſent vnto her the complaintes of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, adding therewyth a byll of ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the nobles, whereby they dyd complayne of ſo great and open iniurye, and requeſted therewyth, that they might performe theyr promiſe of defending the late agréement which they had ſo ſolemnly vowed vnto the people, that no man be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damaged or hurt for hys religion, or for the adminiſtration therof, that the promiſed li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of religion be graunted, that the ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diours
<pb facs="tcp:180997:47"/>
oures gathered contrary to theyr former promiſe and oth, ſhould be diſcharged and diſmiſſed: &amp; laſtly, that the common wealth ſhould be gouerned according to equity and right, and to the couenauntes whereunto they were ſworne. She in her aunſwer maketh many doubtes,<note place="margin">Febru. 16.</note> and ſéeketh the fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacie of wordes, ſaying that there was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing graunted as concerning the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of religion, but only licence geuen for theyr preachinges and ſermons, but as for baptizing of children, and the Lordes ſupper, there was no mention made: ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding therfore that the people had firſt broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theyr couenauntes. Briefly ſhe manifeſtly declareth, that ſhee would no longer be bound vnto theſe couenaunts: but (for ſhe perceaued her ſelfe to be of greater force) that ſhe would gouerne all things after her owne arbitriment: and therwithall ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, that Brederodius, and the reſt of the nobles (which put vp that bill of ſupplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) were the auctors of the ſedition, and therfore, that ſhe dyd accompt them as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels and traytors to the kinges maieſtie, &amp; as enemies of the countrey: and that the king would execute iuſt and condigne pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment vpon them as giltie of thoſe hay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous crimes: and in the meane time ſhe
<pb facs="tcp:180997:47"/>
would vſe her aucthoritie, according as it ſhould beſt pleaſe her.</p>
            <p>Theſe letters ſent to Brederodius, and the other confederate princes, it can not be tolde how greatly they were aſtoniſhed, for they ſaw themſelues moſt openly mocked and deceaued: theyr fidelitie promiſed by oth to the people, nothing eſtéemed: them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues on the one part to be taken for rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious traytors to the kinges maieſtie: and on the other ſide for periured perſons, which w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their vaine promiſes had brought the people into a fooles paradiſe, and made them ſubiect to the ſlaughter, and butcherly fury of theyr aduerſaries: theyr confirmed couenauntes, the kinges name, ſeale, and letters patentes, to be of no force: their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer agréement (by the which as by a bayte they were drawne into the net) to be moſt manifeſtly deluded: and that they were ſo far from hauing licence to cleare and purge them ſelues, that they might not be ſuffred once to entreat, or to make ſupplication for mercy: and that they were openly taken for enemies, enuironed about with ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, ſo that there was no place for them lefte whereby they might eſcape by flying. They being thus at their wittes ende, not knowing which way to take, were compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb facs="tcp:180997:48"/>
at the length in all haſt to muſter theyr ſouldiers, not that they ment to attempt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing as enemies, but that they might ſo long defend the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues from the violence &amp; iniuries of theyr aduerſaries, vntill that they might either get equity for their cauſe, or oportunitie to flie. For if they would o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe haue inuaded the kinges Cities, there is no man ſo great a ſtraunger, or ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noraunt of the matters done in Belgie, which doth not know that many cities ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding theyr Embaſſadors, did require theyr ayde, and deſired that it might be lawfull onely by the graunt and authority of Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derodius, which was the captayne of the confederate princes, to defend themſelues by force of armes againſt the inſolency and violence of theyr aduerſaries. The Valen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenentians required to haue one of the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie for theyr captayne. Many other ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties alſo being the chiefe amongeſt all the reſt, both for theyr power and authoritie, and alſo for the number of theyr Citizens, made the ſame requeſt: and many other alſo, if they had ſo deſired, would haue ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted themſelues to theyr auctority. And yet notwithſtanding they graunted not to any of them, ſo much as by theyr woorde to yéeld to that they required, except vnto the
<pb facs="tcp:180997:48"/>
Buſcoducentians there was one graunted the which ſhould defende the Citie in the kinges name, and of the confederate prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces agaynſt the inſolency of the forreyne ſouldiers, and ſhould make the nobilitie a way if it fortuned to be ſhut vp, all the reſt wer refuſed, not becauſe it was a hard matter for them to kéepe thoſe cities beyng already furniſhed with munition of warre, eſpecially if the prince of Aurice (whome now the aduerſaries do moſt ſhamefully be lye, calling him the auctor of the whole ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition) would but once but haue imagined ſo great an enterpriſe contrary to the wyll of the King and Gouerneſſe, ſéeing that at hys féete almoſt the whole prouince did caſt themſelues downe, with teares beſéeching him to ayd the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt theſe violent théeues and murderers, &amp; moſt periured tyraunts, and that they might commit themſelues, &amp; all theyres into his power and iuriſdiction, He alſo might with a becke eaſely haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned in hys power, not onely Hollande, Zelande, and the countrey of Truceland, all which places he had in hys gouernment beyng of themſelues (as all men knoweth) of hability to conquer the whole prouince, but alſo Antwarpe, Machlym, Buſtoduſe, and many other of the chéefeſt cities. But
<pb facs="tcp:180997:49"/>
that moſt godly Prince would not deſire a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thyng that ſhoulde ſéeme to impeache the Kinges authoritie: but he gaue ſuch godly counſels to the Gouerneſſe, and to the other Cities, the which if they might haue taken place, would haue ſomewhat brideled the furious rage and couetous ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny of the Spaniſh ſubſtitutes, &amp; would haue retayned the whole prouince quietly and peaceably in theyr loyaltie towarde the king: but he could neuer be perſwaded to take armour himſelfe, or to geue licenſe to the citizens to do the ſame. The other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federate princes, as neare as they could did obey hys auctority, and folow his modeſty, but that they were compelled many times by violence and neceſſitie to take armes, not to inuade or ſet vpon any cities, or to do any violence, but onely to withſtand the violence, and to defend themſelues from the inſolency of theyr aduerſaries, and to make themſelues a way to eſcape by force,<note place="margin">The thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Duke of Alua hys co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare who were the authors of theſe tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults in Belgye.</note> if néede ſhould require.</p>
            <p>And theſe thynges truly which we haue reported, were onely done, before the duke of <hi>Aluaye</hi> hys commyng, the whiche truly we haue thought it neceſſary more largely to expreſſe, that all men may know how vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtly our aduerſaries do deale with vs. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb facs="tcp:180997:49"/>
at their luſt and pleaſure, they haue gouerned all thynges and oppreſſed vs full xl. yeares, with moſt extreme tyranny, and the which at length by their crafty and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till deuiſes, haue ſtyrred vp ſuch greuous tempeſtes, that therby, they not onely man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cypated and made bonde our ſelues, our wiues, and children, but haue brought alſo the moſt floriſhyng prouince of Belgie, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to moſt doulfull calamities and beaſtly ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitude. They do not yet for all this ceaſſe to accuſe vs euery where vnto all Princes and people of Europe of moſt horrible crimes, and to lay the faulte and occaſions of all their couetous and miſchieuous do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynges vppon our neckes, complainyng be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke, becauſe we would not with open bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes, and ſtretched out throates, ſubmitte our ſelues to their glaues and ſwoordes. They are gréeued that we are ſafely eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped their handes, and that we haue loſt one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly our riches &amp; poſſeſſions to be deuoured of their gréedy auarice, &amp; that we haue not committed our lyues, our wiues, and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, our ſoules and conſciences,<note place="margin">Of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federacy of the nobles &amp; of the ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plication.</note> to theyr luſt tyranny and impietie. Otherwiſe what is there that they can moſt eſpecially lay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt vs, can they obiect vnto vs the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federate ſocietie of the princes? let therfore
<pb facs="tcp:180997:50"/>
the writynges of the conſpiracie be read, they truly (though we ſhould holde our peace) would declare, that they attempted nothing, did nothyng, nor once thought v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon any other thyng but onely, whereby they might ſhew forth their loyaltie, fideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and due obedience to their kyng, &amp; one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that they might by the power and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of the kyng withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, and ſuppreſſe the crueltie, auarice, and outragious couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of many of the wicked. But if their let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſealed and confirmed with their owne handes &amp; ſeales be of no credite, yet let the effect of their doings be beleued, for whileſt all thyngs were as yet in ſafetie, what was it, which they went about? dyd they not by ſupplication deſire the kyng to diſanull the vnbridled power of the Inquiſition? to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigate the cruelty of the Edictes? and other Edictes for the orderyng of Religion to be eſtabliſhed by the kynges authoritie, and decrée of the eſtates. But verely here is the chief poynte of our aduerſaries accuſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, bycauſe forſooth they beyng frée men, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, louers of their countrey, and deſirous of peace, faythfully addicted to the kynges maieſtie, durſt be ſo bold by humbled ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to require, that the Edictes, whiche were contrary to all equitie, much impea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyng
<pb facs="tcp:180997:50"/>
the kynges dignitie, and diſturbyng the common wealth brought in by errour and by falſe perſwaſion ſhould be made voyde, and that there might be ſome law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full aſſembly of the eſtates or Parliament holden for the good gouernement of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth. Heare we appeale to you, (you moſt mightye Emperour of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines, and to ye all the famous Princes of the Chriſtian Religion) and by that one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and immortall God, and by his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt in whoſe name we pleade our cauſe we humbly deſire you, to geue iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in this poynte, whether we in this poynte ſo greuouſly offended, or rather whether they doe not accompt our iuſt and wholy obedience of duetie in ſtede of great impietie. Truly when the kyng was au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoriſed Duke of Brabant, he by ſolemne othe and faithfull couenaunt promiſed that he would paciently ſuffer &amp; moſt willyngly heare all their complaintes, requeſtes or demaundes what ſoeuer the which ſhould be put vp of the Byſhops, Barones, No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, Cities, or Townes, ſubiect vnto him, either ſeuerally by them ſelues, or ioyntly of them altogether, and as often as they would ſhewe forth their burdens or great oppreſſions, that it ſhould be lawfull for
<pb facs="tcp:180997:51"/>
them to do it, without any daunger or of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and without doubting that he would be angry therewith, and that he would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſuffer any to be troubled for ſo doyng, the which if it ſhould chaunce to happen he promiſed to puniſh ſeuerely all thoſe which may be founde giltie of that offence, and at length after many other thynges he conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth that if he ſhall doe or ſuffer to be done any thyng co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to this oth and promiſe, he deſired forthwith his ſubiectes to be frée from their othe &amp; loyaltie, vntill ſuch tyme that he ſhall fully make them ſatiſfaction in that poynte and in all other matters accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng to this his promiſe . Iudge ye therfore (ye moſt renoumed and puyſaunt Princes whether the nobles by puttyng vp of this their ſupplication haue iuſtly deſerued to haue the kyngs ſo great and heauy diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure agaynſt them and their poor Citizens and frendes. Although who is ſo voyde of all ſence and reaſon and ſo ignoraunt of the affaires of Princes, which doth not know, that it is moſt profitable for kynges &amp; prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that their ſubiectes ſhould moue them by humble ſupplication to prouide for the weale publike, and the ſome ready and fit way ſhould be taken for the good appointe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and ſafe preſeruyng of the common
<pb facs="tcp:180997:51"/>
tranquilitie.</p>
            <p>Who alſo is ignoraunt that theſe frée &amp; ſolemne aſſemblyes be not vſed in all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces, and amongeſt all people,<note place="margin">Of the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles requeſt</note> but alſo accompted as the onely ſtay and remedy of all miſchiefes and publike calamities, and that no man hath at any tyme heretofore gone about, to hynder ſuch ſolemne mée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynges, but they which would robbe and ſpoyle the poore people of the right of their liberties of all their auncient lawes &amp; cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes &amp; fréedome of their priuileges and dyd deſire to rule all alone, accordyng to their lewde luſt and appetite, and by right or by wrong to execute tyranny vpon their poore ſubiectes ſoules &amp; bodyes. This truly is moſt manifeſt that in Germany all the whole maieſtie and honor of their Empire is mainteyned by the due orderyng of their ſolemne parliamentes. Niether hath there any wiſe man doubted but that in all the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther prouinces of all Europe all the ſafety of the people and the dignitie of the prince, hath onely bene preſerued by theſe general aſſemblyes? But in eſpecially in low Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many. It is moſt manifeſt, that the caſe ſo ſtandeth, for in it the princes haue in all ages from tyme to tyme bene ſubiect to the power of the generall Parliamentes, haue
<pb facs="tcp:180997:52"/>
bene elected by them, &amp; confirmed of them, without whoſe aſſent and authoritie they neuer would decrée any thing, and it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly prouided and eſtabliſhed by the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uileges of Brabant and cuſtomes of Flau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, that they neuer haue authoritie to do it hereafter. But ſeyng by their mutuall aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and contract, they be in force of coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nauntes agréed vppon, and hereafter to be taken for their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon law of the countrey, It is of vndoubted credite that the kyng ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>not violate or breake them without the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent of the other parties. Admit it be ſo, the nobles haue offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded in this one pointe, let it be accompted as wickedneſſe vnto them by humble ſupplication to ſhew the way how the common deſtruction of theyr countrey might eaſely haue bene a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyded. Wherin I pray you dyd the poore comminaltie offended, or without crime haue they deſerued ſuch great and accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med crueltie? vnleſſe you will ſay it was, bycauſe they gaue credite to the publike E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictes publiſhed in the kynges name, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed with his broad ſeale, and dyd thinke they might ſafely without all fraude or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit (hauyng for their defence this licence graunted by publike promiſe) hauyng re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to the hearyng of the Goſpell prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched:
<pb facs="tcp:180997:52"/>
for wheras they do accuſe the people of takyng armes, agaynſt their kyng, of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowyng of the images of Churches, of bryngyng a new Religion, their accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is moſt vayne and ſlaunderous?</p>
            <p>For as concernyng their takyng of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more,<note place="margin">Of taking of armour.</note> there was no man which dyd abuſe them agaynſt the kyng or his dignitie, but truly before the publike promiſe and othe was neglected, before the kynges Edictes (wherby the libertie of religion was grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) where violated, before the couenauntes agréed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and the leage of their common tranquilitie was broken, there was no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> went armed, except it were for defence of him ſelfe agaynſt the impudent violence of théeues and murtherers, &amp; the open threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynges of moſt wicked perſons, and that alſo was when they went out of the Cities to the ſermons ſome of them tooke a ſword, ſome a ſtaffe, ſome a ſpeare, very few ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng dagges, euen as one takyng his ior<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney into a farre countrey armeth him ſelfe to withſtand the inuaſions of théeues &amp; cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throtes. But afterwardes when in this pointe they were commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to be ſecure, and that the gouerneſſe had geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in charge that ſhould hurt or indammage them, as long as they kept them ſelues quiet, by and
<pb facs="tcp:180997:53"/>
by, they at the commaundement of their Magiſtrates layd aſide their weapons moſt willyngly, committyng the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues into their to the lawes of God &amp; man, and to all their tuition &amp; ſafegard. But at length whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the promiſed made, &amp; contrary both priuileges, they perceiued them ſelues to be ouercome of the ſouldiours, the which had obteyned full licence to deſtroy them (although they had committed them ſelues to the publicke fayth) and with robberyes, murders, waſtings, rapes, adulteries, &amp; all kynde of wickednes, to rage agaynſt them, as if they were enemies and traytors, then at the length many of them bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to defend them ſelues with gates and walles fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the violent fury of their aduerſaries. Laſt of all when they perceiued neither publike liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, nor their wiues chaſtitie, nor their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences tranquilitie, nor their owne lyues ſafely defended, from their viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, by their gates and walles. Many we confeſſe tooke vpon them armore, not agaynſt the kynges maieſtie, or any Magiſtrates, but rather that they might defend their libertie graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them by the kyngs Edict from the raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of théeues and wicked ſouldiours, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was this done of all men, but of a very few, the whiche when they perceiued no
<pb facs="tcp:180997:53"/>
there hope to eſcape, but onely exile, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame alſo by the wickednes of their aduerſaries to be ſhut vp from them, they thought it beſt by force of armes to make them ſelues ſome way to eſcape by, the which truly if they had not done, and alſo if that the terror of Brerodius ſouldiours had not made theyr aduerſaryes a litle doubtfull, doubtleſſe not one of them from ſo great a ſlaughter had eſcaped ſafe from the gredy iawes of their aduerſaries. They can neuer proue that any other, or that theſe for any other cauſe dyd take vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them armore before the commyng of the Duke of Alba: although they had many and ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry oportunities and occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s offred them, both to poſſeſſe many much and well fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced Cities and alſo to inuade and ſpoyle the kynges treaſure and Excheker. But they would commit nothyng wherof they might not with a ſafe conſcience make rehearſall before God, and all good men. But if any in ſolent perſons either haue gone about or done any other thyng, or for ſome other purpoſe, ſeyng their doinges were neither commaunded nor alowed by thoſe whiche were the chief of the congregation, let not ſo great a multitude of innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t perſons be puniſhed for the inſolencie of a few, for it
<pb facs="tcp:180997:54"/>
doth nothyng apperteine vnto vs, what a few priuate men haue committed for to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge their iniuries taken before either of the Inquiſitors, or of the ſacrificyng prieſts or of any other perſon.<note place="margin">Of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages.</note> Much leſſe doth the ouerthrowyng of Images &amp; Idols apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne vnto vs, for we will eaſely proue that it was done without the commaundement or conſent of our Miniſter Elders or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, vnleſſe a few of ours (percey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng the Magiſtrate to agrée therunto) did thinke it likewyſe lawfull for them to do the ſame, although truly who ſoeuer they were that committed it, they haue bene more then ſufficiently puniſhed for their offence, for in place of one dead and bloc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh Image, their hath bene aboue xxx. liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Images of God (for whom the ſonne of God dyd ſhed hys bloud) murthered de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed and burnt and in ſtede of one rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten blocke, more then ten liuely bodyes, &amp; yet the Images reſtored and renewed by their common charges. As concernyng the new Religion wherof they accuſe vs to bée authours euery man knoweth how farre our religion which we profeſſe is from that kynde of newnes.<note place="margin">Of new re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</note> For beſides that this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was deliuered vnto vs by Chriſt, the antiquitie of all thyngs, the eternall ſonne
<pb facs="tcp:180997:54"/>
of God, by his profites Apoſtles and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs from many ages, it is manifeſt that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue whole fifty yeares it hath floriſhed in Belgie, and bene ſet foorth in priuate mée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynges and Sermons. Neither was it at any tyme, either by any lawfull iudgement or Edict rightly made co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned. For what ſo euer iudgementes hath bene geuen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the profeſſours of this Religion, the iudges them ſelues and Magiſtrates were compelled by the ſeueritie of the Edictes to confeſſe agaynſt their will and with great ſtrife of conſcience to pronounce the ſame. Yea they which were found gilty, were not ſuffred lawfully to defend them ſelues, but they had their mouthes ſtopped with a ball, and theyr tounges cut out of their heades contrary to the true order of Iuſtice. It is manifeſt alſo that all the Edictes whiche were made by <hi>Charles</hi> the Emperour and kyng <hi>Phillip</hi> are voyde and of none effect, bycauſe they were made contrary to the lawes and ſtatutes of the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey, without the counſel and conſent of the eſtates of the prouince required in ſolemne aſſembly (as they were bound by othe thereunto) with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out whoſe aſſent nothyng accordyng vnto the cuſtome and maner of their aunceſtors could be eſtabliſhed, and were alſo thruſt
<pb facs="tcp:180997:55"/>
vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> many of the Magiſtrates agaynſt their will, ſtaiyng them ſelues vpon moſt vayne fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dations, full of friuolous cauils by falſe vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng, as we haue before declared by the euident playne wordes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Edictes. Therfore this religion can not by any ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of meanes be counted a new religion, nor they the profeſſors of the ſame, ſeyng they were vnco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned as yet by any law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full iudgement accuſed of any cryme, much leſſe ſhould they be eſtemed as the authors of ſedition and tumultes of the people, and cauſers of this great &amp; greuous calamitie.</p>
            <p>But what néede we in ſo playne a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to vſe ſo many wordes? ſéeing the caſe doth euidently ſhew it ſelf, and euery man perceyueth who ought to be accuſed as au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of theſe turmoyles &amp; calamities. We haue hertofore declared what was the mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning and intent of the ſpaniſh Inquiſitors, and prieſtes, what counſell they haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, what helpe and miniſters they haue vſed, by what meanes they haue eſpyred vnto thys tyrannicall gouernment, and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne authority in Belgye without any law,<note place="margin">Of thinges done after the Duke of Albas commyng.</note> or preſcript. Though theſe thinges peraduenture (becauſe of theyr great mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtie and equitie, which they vſe in other prouinces) may ſéeme to ſome not probable
<pb facs="tcp:180997:55"/>
(although truely they be dayly ſong in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry childes mouth) yet if he way theſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent tymes, if he ſée the effectes of matters, theſe theyr doinges and affayres, and note this the vncredible tyranny of the Duke of Alba, all which are moſt apparant to all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he ſhall nothing doubt therein.</p>
            <p>All they whom they did call rebels, haue forſaken they countrey, and although they might haue had good occaſions and oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities to kéepe ſome ſtirre, yet they choſe rather voluntary exile, baniſhment, and moſt extreame pouertie, then that they would vexe theyr countrey with moſt dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full warre. But what? haue they any thing for all thys mitigated theyr cruelty? Haue they not after all theſe thinges brought to paſſe in Spayne by theyr deuiſes, that the king (which in a ſolemne aſſembly at Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dride had ſworne, that he woulde in hys owne perſon reuenge the iniury, which he thought himſelfe to haue taken of hys ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes at Belgye, and for that cauſe made all thinges ready for hys iorney, and had fully determined to take his ſonne, and the Quéene hys wyfe wyth hym) ſhould alter hys purpoſe agaynſt his will, and (becauſe they knewe hym by nature to be a Prince prone to all kinde of mercy and gentlenes)
<pb facs="tcp:180997:56"/>
to continue ſtill in Spayne? Haue they not ſubſtituted or ſent an Embaſſador in hys ſtead (the kings ſonne, and many of the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles were vnwilling thereunto) the Duke of Alba, whom by hys nature and maners they well knew to be very fit for theyr pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, both by thoſe thinges which he did in Germany, by the order of hys whoſe lyfe, but eſpecially alſo by the deadly hatred, and rancored grudge which he had of long time layd vp in hys ſtomake agaynſt the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Belgye, for theyr valiaunt actes at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieued in the warres of Fraunce agaynſt his will and meaning. Haue they not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted vnto him the full power and aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, yea haue they no cauſed the kynges onely ſonne, lawfull heyre and Lord of the prouince of Belgye, to end hys lyfe ſhut vp in a moſt horrible priſon, becauſe he was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the ſending of the Albane, and dyd abhorre from the cruelty of the edictes ſette out agaynſt the religion, bearing ſinguler fauour and grace towards the lower Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes, bruting abroad moſt vayne and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers rumors of the cauſe of hys death. What they haue done vnto the Quéene, I had rather other men ſhould imagine, then that we ſhould report.</p>
            <p>This truely all men do behold, how this
<pb facs="tcp:180997:56"/>
theyr faythfull champion the duke of Alba doth behaue himſelfe. He commeth into a quiet prouince, all thoſe beyng thrown out or volu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taryly gone into exile, whom he loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked to haue had as hys aduerſaries. He is receaued moſt honourably of all men, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was there any one found, which with hys moſt redy obedience to the kinges le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate, dyd not teſtifie hys faythfull hart to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the king.<note place="margin">The Duke of Albas doynges ſince his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myng to Belgye.</note> But he out of hand or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth them not as the kinges louing ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes, but as enemies and traytors, equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly raging and extending hys cruelty both v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the profeſſors of the Goſpell, and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes, compelling, he conſtrayned the chéef Princes contrary to the aucthoritye of the lawes, to the liberty of theyr priuiledges, and chiefly contrary to the decrees and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointmentes of the ſacred and famous or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the golden fléece, of the brotherhoode of Burgundye, to plead theyr cauſe in chai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and when they refuſed that kinde of iudgement as vnméete and to be ſuſpected, profering themſelues redy to ſtand before equall Iudges he chopt of theyr heads: the reſt which by their godly and holſome coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels had defended the peace of theyr coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and by theyr wiſedome ſtayd the tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multes of the people, and effuſion of bloud,
<pb facs="tcp:180997:57"/>
he pronounceth as enemies and traytors to theyr king and their contrey, and ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelleth them (will they, nill they) by taking vpon them armour, to try themſelues vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giltie of ſo great treaſon. The which theyr taking of armour (done by them for neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities ſake, as godly men may iudge) he hath ſince that time not only made as a iuſt occaſion of ſlaundring vs with hys cauils, but alſo as a goodly title of Iuſtice in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting hys tyranny: and therupon forthwith he putteth in practiſe that which he had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore determined. Therfore he firſt put all the magiſtrates (which were thought once to fauour iuſtice) out of theyr auctority and place, wyth great ignominy and reproch: he ſubſtituted in theyr roomes, contrary to theyr lawes and orders, naughty packes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounding in all ſinne and wickednes: and he appoynted as be thought good, a new ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate houſe of Spaniardes, before whome matters of lyfe and death ſhould be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, the which for that cauſe ſhould be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the bloudy ſenate, and by that meanes he did depriued all the lawfull and ordinary magiſtrates of theyr iuriſdiction and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of matters graunted to them by the lawes: he filled the gallowes and the Iub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits full of the poore people conuicted of no
<pb facs="tcp:180997:57"/>
other crime, but of geuing credite to the kinges letters patentes, to the gouerneſſe edicte, and theyr graunted licences, and to the magiſtrates conſenting therunto: and thereupon of hearing of ſermons: he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed many with the ſworde, he burned many aliue wyth a ſmall fire, he beheaded many before theyr cauſes we pleaded, many he ſpoyled of all theyr goodes and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions, poyſoned to death with the filthye ſtincke of the continuall priſon. But the vngodly perſons, whoſe whole lyfe had bene ſtayned wyth infamy, being before (as it is manifeſt) bought out with money, haue gaue them licenſe to plead wyth theyr witneſſes, he cut out many of theyr tonges (whome he put to death after) leaſt they ſhould teſtifie of ſo great iniuſtice, he burnt many of theyr tongues with a whot payre of tonges, &amp; to ſome he tyed theyr lippes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether through with an iron, ſharp on both ſides: others hauing theyr mouthes moſt beaſtly ſet awry with terror and anguiſh, the matter and bloud dropping downe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, he cruelly drewe to moſt pytifull ſlaughter. He pretermitted nothing of Pha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>laris his tyranny, neyther did he only wyth tormentes thus vexe the profeſſors of the goſpell, but thoſe alſo which moſt fauoured
<pb facs="tcp:180997:58"/>
the popiſh religion, and they which had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuored with all theyr power, that nothing ſhould be moued agaynſt the king. As for thoſe which could not behold the calamitie of theyr countrey, but had for the auoyding of the preſent dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger conueyed themſelues away, he appoynted them a day of appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce, and therwithall ſcarce ſtaying for the day appoynted, he ruſhed in vpon theyr goodes, adiudging them confiſcate to the kinges Exchequer: not only ſpoyling poore widowes, innocent orphauntes, and very papiſtes of their dowry and patrimony, but alſo deceyuing the creditors of all their iuſt debtes and lawful titles. He conuerted the inheritaunce of innocentes from their kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and alians (to whom for the beheding or ciuill death of the right and next heyres they by law and right did appertayne) moſt wickedly to hys owne vſe and commoditie. He tooke from cities and townes, all theyr liberties, lawes, ſtatutes, &amp; priuiledges, he ouerthrew all order of humanitie, he cleare<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly tooke away all duties of Chriſtian chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye, chiefly commaunded by the lawes of God. For by edict he forbad that no kinde of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whether he were their father, ſonne kinſman, or whatſoeuer, ſhould ſhew any kinde of charitie to thoſe that profeſſed the
<pb facs="tcp:180997:58"/>
Goſpell, or were baniſhed for default of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearaunce at the day appoynted: and thus he alienated and withdrew the mindes of children from theyr parentes, of parentes from theyr children, and of wiues from theyr huſbandes.</p>
            <p>In the towne of Traciet of Moſa, he put a father to death, becauſe he had for one night lodged in hys houſe his owne ſonne, which had bene for a ſpace abſent before. And likewyſe, he murthered an other well known citizen, becauſe he gaue the ſixt part of a <abbr>bꝪ.</abbr> of corne vnto a poore widow, burde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the kéeping of iiij. children, whoſe huſband was before put to death for reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions ſake. He bereaued alſo an other of hys lyfe, becauſe he ſent hys fréend a little money ouer into England. He compelled honeſt and chaſt matrones borne of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull ſtockes, by flight and voluntary ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ile to ſaue themſelues, and by begging to prouide meat for themſelues and theyr chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, only becauſe they receaued their huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandes into theyr houſes. He threw down many mens houſes, becauſe they had recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued letters from theyr frends of their helth and welfare. But what? did ſpare the dead? By hys Edict he ſtraightly charged, that whoſoeuer dyed without ſhrift and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricular
<pb facs="tcp:180997:59"/>
confeſſion, his goodes ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſcate, and hys body hanged on a Iubbit, then the which what can be thought or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented more cruell, more contrary to all humanitie and Iuſtice? ſéeing it hapeneth daily that many ſodenly that haue no time to bethinke them of theyr former ſinnes. He placed ouer cities not ſouldiers, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies and theues, which might violently abuſe the riches, wiues, children, and liues of the citizens according to theyr euill luſt: and he graunted them licence to do what ſhould pleaſe them fréely without puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: for was there any wickednes ſo hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous, the which the fury of the ſpaniſh ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diours hath not committed in Belgye, and doth dayly commit vnpuniſhed. In Iperis a famous towne in Flaunders, when a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of Gods woord was ſuffring death, the ſouldiers wythout any other occaſion turned theyr weapons vpon the miſerable and vnarmed people ſtanding about them, and beſides an infinite number whom they wounded vnto death, there were xiij. citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens ſhot through with pellettes of leade, which they left dead in the ſtreates.</p>
            <p>At Turnace a diſſention happenyng be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene the Spaniſh ſouldiers, &amp; thoſe other ſouldiers which were there for the defence
<pb facs="tcp:180997:59"/>
of the Caſtle, and two of the Spanyardes beyng ſlayne, the reſt cryed out, Spayne, Spayne, at the which voyce, the other Spa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſh ſouldiers beyng called did runne moſt furiouſly lyke madde men through the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and kylled all whom they met in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber about xv. of godly and honeſt Citizens. In the ſame night ſome of the Spaniſhe ſouldiers, beyng perſuaded that a certaine widow called by the name of her huſband, widow Potier had a great ſomme of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney in her houſe, brake into her houſe ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce at noone dayes, &amp; moſt cruelly murtheryng her, her daughter &amp; néece, they caryed out of her houſe all thynges they could finde. At Inſull one of the chiefeſt ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of all Flaunders, which hath bene al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes moſt addicted to the popiſh religion, when a Spanyard going about by violence to rauiſh an honeſt citize<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s wife, was let of his purpoſe by her huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d &amp; ij. of his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, he cryed out Spayne, (a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon by word amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the auoydyng of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent daunger in their wicked enterpriſes,) the other ſouldiers warned with that out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cry, came runnyng and by force &amp; viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, apprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded the Citizen and his two neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and deliuered them vnto the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate to be puniſhed lyke rebels and ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb facs="tcp:180997:60"/>
perſons, with his threatnyng, that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they did execute their commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſpedely they would ſet the whole Citie on fire, wherwith the Iudges beyng terrified, cauſed two of them to be hanged, and the thyrd to be whipped. But what auayleth it to recken vp particularly all the wickednes which the Spaniſhe ſouldiers haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, ſeing their can not be imagined any offence ſo haynous, the which they do not day by day commit fréely, without any pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, and yet the Duke of <hi>Alba</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelleth them to mainteine theſe ſouldiers at their owne proper coſtes and charges. Belyke that they might ſpoyle and robbe their coffers, rauiſh their wiues, kill their children and families at their pleaſure, and leauyng nothyng frée from their crueltie, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarice and horrible wickednes, then the whiche what can be imagined more vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt? although truly there is no iniuſtice ſo great, from the which the <hi>Alba</hi> Duke doth abhorre, for leaſt he ſhould leaue any thyng holy &amp; vnpoluted, with his beaſtly boldnes he dareth prophane the moſt holy rightes of matrimony: he hath diſſolued (vnder the vayne pretence of hereſie) the lawfull ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages of many, and made their children be gotten in iuſt mariage, to be taken for ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtardes
<pb facs="tcp:180997:60"/>
&amp; as illegittimate, to be excluded fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſucceſſion of their patrimony: he ioyned other mens wiues, (which were maryed before in the open aſſembly of the Church) to other men by a new mariage, or rather, by moſt infamous adultery, becauſe they had omitted a maſſe, of that the Prieſt was not curteouſly enterteyned at his comming to them: &amp; therwith by his publike Edictes he made manifeſt adultery and open biga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to be accompted lawfull. He hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled widowes agaynſt their willes and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly denyeng and withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng the ſame, by force and viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to be maryed vnto his ſouldiers &amp; cutthrotes, in ſomuch that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> choſe rather to forſake their coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>treys, with the loſſe of all their riches, then once to conſent vnto ſuch haynous villany. But what? hath he left the moſt holy Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of Baptiſme vnuiolated? he hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded with great impiety, contrary to all the Popes decretals, that all they, which were baptiſed after the maner of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles in the primitiue Church &amp; accordyng to the iuſt preſcript of the woorde of God ſhould be baptiſed agayne. For what auay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth it to ſpeake of the moſt reuerent order and religious kéepyng of the ſepulchers &amp; graues of thoſe which be buried, the which
<pb facs="tcp:180997:61"/>
from the begynnyng of the world hath ben amongeſt the moſt barbarous &amp; fierce peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple moſt religiouſly kept, ſeyng he hath no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng feared with moſt brutiſh crueltie to breake vp the graues of thoſe godly and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Citizens, which had bene buryed in the ground aboue xiiij. dayes before, and to take out their bodyes ſcarſe cleauyng to the bones, hangyng ſome on gybbets and burning the reſt with fire, neither ſuffered he the cities of the noble Empire to eſcape frée from this his odious kynde of cruelty, for who doth not know that euen at Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deruicke in Geldria, (which is the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours lawfull inheritaunce) there was the body of an honeſt Citizen which had bene buryed long before, drawen out of hys graue, and cruelly pluckt in péeces vnder a gybbet with great and bitter triumphyng before the doore, and euen in the very ſight of the miſerable widow. But what is there holy amongeſt the lyuyng, or religious a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt the dead, the which he hath feared openly to violate and polute, the which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his owne luſt &amp; appetite hath made pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane thynges holy, and holy thynges pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, hath made &amp; abrogated lawes, hath ſpoiled the wealthieſt of all their ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, hath reprochfully ſlaundered the chiefeſt of
<pb facs="tcp:180997:61"/>
the nobilitie, hath put to death thoſe which were moſt innocent, hath deſtroyed féeble old men, younge men, and tender virgines with moſt horrible tormentes, hath oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Cities and the whole prouince with vncredible exactions and vnaccuſtomed tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes, which hath wrong into his handes with his threatnynges an infinite maſſe of gold and ſiluer, and now exacteth ouer all marchaundizes and vſuryes the x. penny, and by that meanes hath diminiſhed the trade of Marchauntes and taken away all lice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of trafique with other natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. Was there euer any tyranny ſince the firſt age of man ſo cruell and ſo couetous as this is? The wicked extorcions, new and vnaccu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed tributes wherewith <hi>Caligula</hi> dyd oppreſſe his ſubiectes are recorded in hyſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes, yet notwithſtandyng he appoynted a meane and meaſure of his couetouſnes, for he aſſigned to euery kynde of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by name their ſeuerall tributes, but his felow, leaſt any thyng ſhould eſcape hym be it neuer ſo litle, beſides the hundredes, which he hath alredy taken away, and the new hundredes which he hath of late commaunded to be le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyed of all their landes, farmes, and other immoueables, he doth exact the x. in all kind of faculties, &amp; beſides all this, he requireth
<pb facs="tcp:180997:62"/>
xx. hundreth thouſand crownes of gold, to be payd him yearely of the whole prouince. What néede we any more, is there any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo cruelly woode or outragious of mynde, that he doth not tremble and quake at the foden remembraunce of this vnaccuſtomed crueltie, auarice, vnfaythfulnes, and impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie? or can there any man be found ſo voyde of ſenſe and reaſon, whoſe vnderſtandyng is ſo blynded, that he beleueth that theſe good and well diſpoſed perſons, doth ſéeke nothyng els, but to kéepe the prouince of Belgie vnder the kynges authoritie, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend religion, and mainteyne lawes? ſeyng all their actions and doinges do openly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend &amp; ſhew, that they haue no other kyng, no law, or religion, but their onely auarice, and moſt beaſtly couetouſnes, they make a glorious pretence, as though all the Belgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans were Lutherans, rebelles, and tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors to the kyngs maieſty, bycauſe forſooth, they would not ſubmit their neckes to the yocke of the Inquiſition, that is to ſay they would not willyngly and of their owne ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord yeld vp them ſelues, to the beaſtly luſt, and vniuſt tyranny of moſt pernicious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. But truly if they had their kyng for theyr enemy, they would neuer haue ſo faythfully obſerued their loyalty towardes
<pb facs="tcp:180997:62"/>
him, neyther would they ſo carefully haue retained all their cities, townes, and caſtels in hys fidelitie &amp; tuitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: neyther would they ſo faithfully haue geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> credite to the kyngs edictes, the kynges name, the kinges brode ſeale, &amp; to the Gouerneſſe, and in ſo doyng ſhould neuer haue runne into ſo many &amp; ſo great calamities by their ſo light credulity: neither ſhould the Duke of Alba once haue ſet foote into theſe countryes: for they had infinite occaſions and oportunities offered them of diſſanulling the kinges authoritie, of alienating hys cities, of ſtriking league with other nations adioyning vnto them, and of kéeping backe the Alban duke from the borders of theyr prouince: And yet for all thys dare not the aduerſaries affirme (vnleſſe they be moſt impudent) that thys was once mentioned amongſt them or ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of. But let it be ſo that they were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, is it lawfull therfore for the King to violate hys faithfull promiſe, to peruert the lawes both of God and man, and to pollute all thinges both holy, and prophane, wyth thys vnaccuſtomed tyranny?</p>
            <p>We read that in the time of our aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, many of the cities of Flaunders dyd rebell agaynſt Maximilian the moſt mighty king of the Romanes, and the citizens dyd
<pb facs="tcp:180997:63"/>
not onely openly refuſe hys gouernement, and deteyned wyth them for the ſpace of eight yeares his ſonne Philippe againſt his will, but alſo did moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tumeliouſly throw Maximilian himſelfe into priſon, but after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes beyng ouercome by the helpe of Frederike the Emperour, and other the princes of Germany, they yelded the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues agayne to hys authoritie: then thys good prince Maximilian in thys ſo odious rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, and hauing bene ſo iniuriouſly hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, was ſo farre from doing any thing lyke vnto the Albane Duke, that he not onely with great gentlenes receaued hys ſubiects agayne into his graces fauor, but alſo with great clemency worthy of ſo great a prince reſtored vnto them agayne all theyr priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges and auncient immunities. By the which hys vncredible lenitye, he made the hole prouince moſt obedient in all pointes to hym, and hys poſteritie for euer. But theſe men neuer remitted any tribute, any ſubſedy, or burden, layd vppon the kinges moſt faythfull ſubiectes, whoſe loyaltie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the King, coulde neuer wyth any crime be attayned, beyng alwayes obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to the kinges commaundement, who had offered vp by humble ſupplication all theyr riches and ſubſtaunce vnto the kings
<pb facs="tcp:180997:63"/>
good will and pleaſure, deſiring to haue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing frée from the Kinges commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but onely a cleare conſcience in reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, the which they ought to kéepe vnpol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted vnto God alone. And they humbly deſired to redéeme the libertie of religion with an extraordinary and farre more grée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous tribute, then the Chriſtians redéeme theyr religion of the Turke, or the Iewes obtayne theyrs of the pope. Yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding theſe men (I ſay) ſpoyling thoſe faythfull ſubiectes of all theyr riches, forbid them the vſe of fyre and water, ayre &amp; land, as if they were the moſt deadly enemies of all mankinde: &amp; yet haue they (God know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth) committed no offence, but only geuen to light credite to the kings edicts, which in manner were eſtabliſhed as firme lawes, &amp; neuer to be reuoked, and ſo they ſimply be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leuing the kinges letters and name, kept diligently their ſermons, in the which there was nothing preached but the pure woorde of God, and they dayly admoniſhed to ſhew theyr obedience to the prince and his magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates. Yet theſe tyrantes doth with moſt horrible cruelty oppreſſe the hole prouince without reſpect either of the innocent or of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders, and wyth moſt inſatiable auarice ſpoyling them, torment them wyth moſt
<pb facs="tcp:180997:64"/>
barbarous tyranny.</p>
            <p>Can any man now doubt, what it is that theſe men haue hertofore laboured to bring to paſſe, or whereunto they haue bended theyr mindes, ſet theyr eyes, and applyed theyr moſt reuening handes? Or is there any man ſo blind that can not ſée what hath bene the cauſe &amp; originall of theſe foreſayd tumultes in Belgye, or ſo blockiſh that he can not perceiue that theſe honeſt men, I meane the good maiſters and byſhops of the ſpaniſh inquiſition, haue from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, onely gone about to alienate the kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges minde from hys ſubiectes, and by eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſmall or none occaſion to accuſe them of rebellion, that as they haue moſt furiouſly executed theyr tyranny in the kingdome of Naples, Cycell, and the countrey of Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, in new India, and in the chiefeſt par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of Spayne: ſo they might by ſome ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of meanes furiouſlye rage in the lowe Germany, and by litle and litle when occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſhall bee offered, in highe Germany: and that vnder the colour of defending the Popes religion, they might oppreſſe the hole libertie of the citizens in Belgie, take away theyr magiſtrates authoritie, and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olate the hole power of theyr lawes, bring the kinges maieſtie ſubiect to theyr autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritye,
<pb facs="tcp:180997:64"/>
and that they themſelues might with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out law or order at their pleaſure co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maund what they wyll, take what they lyſte, kyll whatſoeuer ſhould offend them, empty the rich mens coffers, and make themſelues lordes and gouernors of all thinges.</p>
            <p>But if any man ſhall thinke that theſe thynges, becauſe they be preſent,<note place="margin">Of thinges done in Ger<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>many and in other places heretofore.</note> &amp; not yet throughly finiſhed, can not eaſily be iudged vpon, let hym coniecture, and take iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thynges alredy paſt. In the which we appeale vnto your maieſties, moſt mighty Emperour, and ye renowmed prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Germany, call to remembraunce, what they haue heretofore done in Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many, what with what fetches and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelles they haue wrought, you ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue truly theyr old artes, you ſhall know theſe old Spaniardes you ſhall know theſe old Inquiſitors, for eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe be they which with their greuous cauils and ſclaunders, &amp; with the terror of the Popes name haue oppreſſed the moſt famous princes of Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many before <hi>Charles</hi> the v. which kyndled a moſt dolefull firebrand of ciuill diſſention in the very bowels of hygh Germany, and vnder the cloake of rebellion, dyd ſet the Proteſtant Princes together by the eares, beyng altogether ignoraunt of their treche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
<pb facs="tcp:180997:65"/>
the which haue defiled all things in Ger<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>many with their wicked &amp; flagitious actes, the whiche haue gone about to ouerthrow the liberties of Germany and lawes of the Empire, and euen theſe be they at this day whiche do vexe and trouble the inhabiters of low Germany with the very ſame ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils, before the foreſayd <hi>Charles</hi> his ſonne kyng of Spayne, they haue deceiued them with the ſame artes and ſubtilties, and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed with the ſame enterpriſes, theſe be the authors &amp; inuentors of ſo great vnfayth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fulnes, theſe alſo be giltie of their crueltie &amp; auarice, theſe were the miniſters and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of all their miſchieuous boldnes. For to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is Granduellanus the Cardinall of the Germaynes vnknowen, or who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not the Duke of <hi>Alba?</hi> both the which haue empriſoned the moſt noble princes of Germany, ouercommyng them partly by violence, and partly by their fraude and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyte, and haue ſlaundered them with moſt reprochful contumelyes. Theſe be the fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brandes of the whole world, with the which the greateſt part of Europe, will moſt dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully be ſet a fire, vnleſſe your authoritie wiſedome and power, do with ſpéede fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſée ſo great a miſchief, theſe men therfore are onely to be accompted as the authors
<pb facs="tcp:180997:65"/>
of all the tempeſtuous broyles ſeditions tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multes &amp; miſerable calamities which haue happened in Belgye. But if there be any man that doth not as yet vnderſtand, let hym remember the ſaying of Caſſianus (to whom theſe thynges ſhall profite) &amp; let hym diligently conſider not onely to whom this publicke calamitie of Belgy is now profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but alſo if there be any hope, that theſe thyngs will be profitable to hym hereafter. Seyng we could not but perceiue that this daunger was iminent either by loſſe of our religion or by woundyng of our conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, or by the greuous anger of our kyng, or by the dolefull deſtruction of our countrey, whiche way ſoeuer it would haue happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. For they haue long ago hunted after their triumphes, theyr ruledome and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyre by any theſe occaſions. So that they neuer haue ceaſed by theyr ſubtill deuiſes to cauſe the ſubiectes to hate theyr kyng, &amp; the kyng likewiſe to hate his ſubiectes, and with gréedy mouthes &amp; ſtretched out eares they haue take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the leſt ſuſpition of tumults and rebellion, and haue filled the kynges eares and mynde wyth theyr falſe tales, odiouſly amplifying their receiued newes, the which though it be ſo manifeſtly to all men that it néede no longer proufe yet it is
<pb facs="tcp:180997:66"/>
moſt manifeſtly confirmed by the kynges Embaſſadors which was ſent into Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce,<note place="margin">A copye of this Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle worde for word is to be ſeene in the end of the duke of Au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ces Apologye confirmed with all their ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des</note> for he in his letters ſent to the gouernours writeth on this wiſe, their will aryſe vnto the king great frute and commoditie by the incommodious tumultes of Belgy, becauſe by this occaſion, the kyng will bryng them to full obedience and ſubiection, and reduce the ſtate into that forme and order of gouer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment vnto the which hys auncetors could neuer atteyne, the which to bryng to paſſe, the kyng hath vehemently deſired of longe tyme, and therein hath alwayes hetherto ſpent hys whole ſtudy and endeuour, and that there was no man, (fauouryng the kynges maieſty,) would counſell him to let paſſe ſo noble occaſion of the performau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of this his woorthy enterpriſe, &amp;c. By the which wordes it is manifeſtly declared that the Spaniſhe Inquiſitors (whiche in the name of the kyng doe cloake and couer all their deſires) haue ſought and gone about heretofore to get any occaſion, whereby they might inuade Belgy ſpoyle it of all his riches and goodes, and rule all thynges as ſhould beſt be thought to their luſt and plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure. So that no man can longer doubt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence theſe haue had theyr begynnyng, ſeyng it is manifeſt who they are that haue
<pb facs="tcp:180997:66"/>
long ago deſired to reape the frutes of theſe our troubles, &amp; it is alſo manifeſt that the Cardinall hym ſelfe in a great aſſembly of many men, when it was obiected vnto hym that it was to be feared leſt if the people ſhould be any more oppreſſed they would make ſome ſedition, was not aſhamed to aunſwere, that the kyng had no cauſe to feare, But rather to wiſh for the ſeditious tumultes of his ſubiectes: for by them the kynges power and maieſtie was much en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, and the priuileges of the Cities &amp; liberties of the people very much reſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and diminiſhed. Otherwiſe, what is it that they ſhould ſeeke for by ſo many exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of ſuch vnaccuſtomed auarice &amp; rare crueltie: would they make the people ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to the kynges authoritie? euery wiſe man ſéeth, that then they take not the iuſt and right way to obteyne they purpoſe. For the ſubiectes hartes are wonne and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to their prince by gentilnes, huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, and Iuſtice, not by terror, feare, or tyranny: and euery man knoweth, that the prince of Egmonde and an infinite num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of others which haue bene alwayes &amp; euer were moſt earneſt fauourers of the kynges name and authoritie, &amp; they which neuer ſpared the ſweate of their browes or
<pb facs="tcp:180997:67"/>
bloud of their bodyes for to kéepe the whole prouince ſafe in the kynges ſubiection, and whom the king for this cauſe hath alwayes very much regarded, were notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng deſtroyed of them for an old hatred conceyued thorough an old enuie of theyr noble actes ſo worthely atchiued in theyr warres: But peraduenture they ſéeke by this meanes vtterly to roote out the religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the goſpell, which they (though the moſt part of them be of no religion) fayne them ſelues ſo vtterly to deteſte &amp; abhorre. Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they meane nothyng leſſe, for then what cauſe had they with ſuch infamy &amp; reproch cruelly to put to death the foreſayd Prince of Egmonde, the Earle Hornam, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others, which were both ignoraunt of this Religion, and haue bene alwayes ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaryes of the ſame: why do they ſtill exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute ſuch tyranny, vpon thoſe which be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together of the Popes religion: but (moſt noble Princes) they deſire nothyng leſſe: their onely fetch is to eſtabliſhe their kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in Belgy, that they may rule therein all thynges accordyng to their lewde luſt &amp; pleaſure, and contrary to all equitie and right, as they haue done, heretofore in Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell and in the kyngdome of Naples, that they beyng loden with the riche ſpoyles of
<pb facs="tcp:180997:67"/>
ſo wealthy a prouince, may returne home, and ſend others in their ſteade, they which ſhould draw them dry of all their iuyce and bloud, there is one onely way to attayne to this purpoſe, and that is their holy Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, the which by good right is termed af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the name of Inquiſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for by this they doe dayly inquyre and make ſearch in the chéeſtes, bagges &amp; coffers of the riche men, in the bewty and boſomes of the virgynes and matrones, in the throtes, bowels and bloud, and laſtly in the ſoules &amp; conſciences of all men, by this they make them ſelues Lordes and Monarches of all thynges they make all the princes and the kyng him ſelfe ſubiect and obedient vnot them, they haue vſed this meanes firſt in Spayne, in the which by this arte of Inquiſition they haue diſanulled all priuileges and libertyes, the which where before very great in Spayne, they haue made ſubiect vnto them ſelues, all the authoritie of lawes and the maieſtie of the regall ſcepter, they haue left onely a bare name and title to the Kyng with part of the taſkes and ſubſides, they challenge vnto them ſelues ſoueraigne rule and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, and in cauſes capitall they appoint vnto the giltie either lyfe or death at theyr owne arbitrement, whom they determine
<pb facs="tcp:180997:68"/>
to deſtroy, no man is able to ſaue, no not the kyng hym ſelfe though he moſt earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſire it, whom they take vpon them to defend, neither the ſeueritie of the lawes, nor Iudgement ſincerely geuen nor the kynges commaundement is hable once to hurt hys litle finger, therfore it is no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayle, if all eſtates, yea and the kynges them ſelues be very much afrayde of them; After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes they folowed the ſame way in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, Cicell, Myllen, and in the great coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey of Indya, &amp; they openly (but in vayne) put the ſame practiſe for to make ſubiect to them ſelues all Germany, for they were withſtode and preue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted by your wiſedome (moſt mighty princes) and by the wiſdome power, and vertue of your auncetors: but yet they ceaſe not at thys time by theyr craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye wiles &amp; deceites, to peforme that which they haue ſo long deſired.</p>
            <p>For that I may pretermit the Gronyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans, the wiſe Phriſians, the Tranſiſelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Geldrians, Remanicenſians, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other of the empyre, the which alwayes haue obayed to the iuriſdiction of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Emperor, haue vſed hys lawes and ſtatutes, and haue appealed to the court of the Emperor, and ſubmitted themſelues into the gouernment of the Duke of Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant,
<pb facs="tcp:180997:68"/>
onely vpon thys condition, that they might retayne theyr lawes, cuſtomes, and ſtatutes faſtly without any appearing of the ſame, all which the Duke of Alba hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued of all theyr liberties and priuileges, and (as though they had bene ouercomme by battell) appoynted them new lawes, cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated new magiſtrates contrary to theyr au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient maner and conſtitution, hath exacted vnaccuſtomed tributes, hath built caſtelles in theyr cities, hath baniſhed the chiefe of theyr citiezens, ſeaſed vp theyr goodes: that I may (I ſay) pretermit all theſe thinges, and infinite more of like ſort, in the which although he hath no right or title, yet he pretendeth to haue ſome kinde of intereſt. For what ende (I pray you) doth he ſéke openly to enlarge the bondes of hys go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment without any iuſt or ſhadowed ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle therunto, euen into the very middeſt of the empyre? What cauſeth him to ſéeke, or rather by force to take vppon hym the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of the countrey of Cleueland, &amp; threatningly to commaund them to baniſh out of theyr countrey, all the Belgians? What cauſeth hym by preſcript to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund Collyn, and the other frée cities of the Empier, what they ſhould do vnto the low Germaynes? It is impoſſible that it
<pb facs="tcp:180997:69"/>
ſhould not be reuealed vnto you (moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy princes) what crueltie he hath commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, what fieldes he hath deſtroyed, what droues of beaſts he hath caried away, what matrones and virgins he hath defloured, how many inhabitauntes he hath murdred in the Eaſt contrey of Phriſia, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey of Emdon? What ſhould we thinke moreouer, ſéeing he doubteth not by hys e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicte to call home all the ſtudentes of low Germany, which were gone abroad to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren vniuerſities, whatſoeuer (onely Rome excepted:) and all the young men which were departed to other places for the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of ſome arte or manuell occupation, threatning perpetuall baniſhment and loſſe of all theyr goodes if they do not returne, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that he hath ſpoyled the poore yong men trauelling abroad for the knowledge of tongues, and getting of wiſedome, of the fruite of all theyr ſtudies and labourers, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them vnfit hereafter to take office vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon them in the common wealth, and hath vtterly beggered and vndone many which trauayled abroad to gette theyr lyuing by theyr arte and occupation. In the whych he ſheweth hymſelfe vtterly to denounce all humanitie: for if all humanitie be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned by the mutuall ſocietie and compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb facs="tcp:180997:69"/>
of men, muſt he not néedes be the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my therof, which by violence ſeketh to take away that one gift, wherby man only ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth himſelf to differ from the brute beaſtes. For the knowledge of tonuges, and vſe of reaſon, althought it be peculiarly geuen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to man, yet the fruit therof is not fully rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, but in the company and ſociety of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; eſpecially in our affayres which we haue with other nations. Therfore ſéeing he go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth about to bereue vs therof, what ſéeketh he els but to deſtroy the toung, &amp; the whole vſe of reaſon: the which truely (ſo great is hys inhumanity) he would do, if he could bring it by any meanes to paſſe. For what other thing doth he ſéeke by this his Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition? Why doth he forbid the people the vſe of holy Scripture? Why doth he refuſe onely the knowledge of Gods holy wil and Teſtament to the deuines, that is forſooth, to his Inquiſitors and byſhops? Why doth he forbidde the people to pray in a knowne tongue? but that he deſireth rather to rule brutiſh beaſtes, then reaſonable men. For he feareth, leſt if they ſhould vnderſtand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing, they would at the length deteſt ſo great &amp; vnaccuſtomed barbarouſnes, and therfore he will haue no cities or countries gone vnto, but thoſe vnto whom he preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth
<pb facs="tcp:180997:70"/>
lawes and ordinaunces. It hath bene very well by the wyſe iudgement &amp; doyngs of our au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cetors brought to paſſe, that you<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g men ſtudious in good literature, and liberal artes, ſhould trauel vnto other vniuerſities to ſée their cities and maners, and to learne their toungues, and for thys cauſe, by the liberality and coſtes of kynges &amp; Princes, frée Vniuerſities were founded, and great libertyes &amp; priuiledges graunted to them, that thether the young men of other coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryes might more often reſort, and that by thys meanes the fayth, frendſhip, and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietie of men among themſelues might the better be retayned: the which truely is no new cuſtome, but hath bene vſed hertofore in all ages. For we read that Platoe, and the other philoſphers dyd wyth long &amp; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers trauellinges learne their wiſedomes, whereof we all ſtand now in admiration, &amp; from ſtraunge peoples and far nations car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the knowledge therof into Grece. The Romanes before times vſed to ſende theyr children into Gréece and Aſia for learnings ſake, and that I may not onely ſtay in thoſe olde examples, not much before the imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of the Turke had ouerrun all Gréece, the Germaynes, Frenchmen, Italians, &amp; the Spanyardes them ſelues were wont
<pb facs="tcp:180997:70"/>
earneſtly to go to Athenes for ſtudy ſake. The which libertie or cuſtome who ſoeuer taketh away, he taketh truly away all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitie and profeſſeth him ſelfe the deadly enemy of all other nations. For it is wont to be forbydden that any Citizen ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habite or dwell amongeſt thoſe, agaynſt who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our Haroldes haue denounced warre, the whiche for this cauſe is done, becauſe we thinke it not lawfull for our Citizens &amp; young men to reſorte to thoſe people, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we accompt as enemyes, ſeyng therefore (right noble Princes) that he doth forbyd his Citizens &amp; frée yong men to be brought vp amongeſt you, &amp; all other nations, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Rome excepted, what ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> otherwiſe be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, but that he miſdoubteth your faith, and ſuſpecteth your meanyng, &amp; deſireth to deale with you, as with his open enemyes. Let therfore all méetynges of marchants &amp; chaunge of marchaundiſes be taken away, let all your Vniuerſities be deſtroyed, abro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gate all their priuileges, ſuffer no hoſopitali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to be kept, let euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſit idle at home, in his owne houſe, take hede leſt any thyng be brought in from farre cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>treys, leſt like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ye bryng in ſomewhat which may at length hynder the barbarous trade of the Duke of Alba.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:180997:71"/>But we hope (moſt worthy princes) that you playnly ſée what me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are chiefly to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed of this our iniury, the Spanyard will not ſuffer our you<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g men to come vnto your Vniuerſities, your ſolemne martes or fayres, or to any of your prouinces, leaſt peraduenture they ſhould returne infected of ſome ſpot of hereſie. By the which hys iudgement he openly condemneth you and all your people of hereſie, and impietie. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in this his doyng, he hath beſides this an other fetch and purpoſe: for this is a new inuention for to ſpoile the poore peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of their ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, for when he ſéeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to haue eſcaped the gréedy iawes of his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition, and it is not eaſie for hym to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe them, beyng abſent, although many of them, in his iudgement, woorthely be accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of ſuch haynous crymes, and had deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to haue their goodes confiſcate, bycauſe they were very rich &amp; wealthy, he thought beſt to deuiſe ſome way whereby he mgyht lykewiſe draw them into his net. And ther fore he ſtretcheth out the vale of his Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, the which he abuſeth to the full ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieng of all his appetites, as <hi>Gigas</hi> dyd hys ryng. By this he driueth ſome out of theyr countrey, and maketh ſome returne home agaynſt their wils. By this he taketh from
<pb facs="tcp:180997:71"/>
ſome all their liberties, riches, and life, to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers he geueth full lycence to praye vpon other mens goodes, and with all wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to ſhed the innocent bloud, to be brefe, vnder this pretence of Religion, he doth what ſoeuer pleaſeth him, though it be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the lawes of God and man. By this alſo, with moſt extreme and vnaccuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny, he goeth about to eſtabliſh &amp; to geue all ſoueraigne power in low Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny vnto the Biſhops of the Spaniſh Inqui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that from thence, if it be poſſible: they might ſtretch the ſame, by their deceytes &amp; priuy practiſes, throughout all Europe.</p>
            <p>Do not you thinke,<note place="margin">Theſe thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges pertain as well to the Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans as to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Belgia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.</note> (moſt noble Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces) that theſe thynges nothyng perteine vnto you: for they do moſt eſpecially bende theyr force agaynſt you, and your Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. For their remayneth as yet, yea there is noriſhed (I ſay) in the Spanyardes harts and bowels the great grief, which they of late conceyued, when they ſaw the gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Germany, (wherof they thought them ſelues in full poſſeſſion) to be pluckt out from betweene theyr iawes. They do as yet trye their old counſelles, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they may make ſubiect all the world to theyr holy Inquiſition, and reteine vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues the full ſuperioritie of all things,
<pb facs="tcp:180997:72"/>
they haue not as yet buryed their old artes and craftie pollicies, they haue not as yet aboliſhed their leages, ſocietyes, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracies: wherby they bounde them ſelues vtterly to ſubuerte all thoſe, whom they thought would withſtand the encreaſe of theyr tyranny. Who doth not know the con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ditions of peace betwene the kynges of Fraunce and Spayne? Who knoweth not the confederacie made with the Bayo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niandes? who knoweth not what fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brandes hath from thence bene brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Fraunce, low Germany, Italye, Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Scotland, and into the furtheſt coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey of all the lande Thule. Truely that longe and deadly ciuill warre in Fraunce was firſt moued and made by theſe authors contrary to the Edictes made by the eſtates of the whole Realme, and contrary to the will of the Kyng and Quéene, and by theſe alſo, the peace beyng broken, the leages violated, and the fidelitie of their othes and agréementes beyng troden vnder féete. It was begon agayne the ſecond and the thyrd time, &amp; by theſe men it hath bene continued almoſt ten yeares, to the great calamitie of that noble prouince, &amp; the great ſlaughter of worthy men and noble princes. Neither do they now at this tyme ceaſſe with theyr
<pb facs="tcp:180997:72"/>
peſtiferous cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſels &amp; moſt wicked practiſes by all their power to breake &amp; make voyde the peace appointed and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluded with the full good will of the kyng &amp; all good men. It is more manifeſt then that it néedes rehear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall what perſecutions they haue done in I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taly, what conſpiracies they made in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, what ſeditious tumultes &amp; murthers they haue cauſed in Scotland, &amp; what rebel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lions they haue raiſed in Irela<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, for what, haue they doubted euen in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, ſettyng vp their Popes buls conuiciouſly to call the moſt noble gratious and vertuous Quéene of England, the ſeruaunt of all wickednes, the mainteyner of moſt wicked perſons an hereticke &amp; fauourer of all heretickes, &amp; do pronounce her curſed by the Popes curſe, to depriue her of the right of her kingdome, and iuriſdiction to abſolue her ſubiectes &amp; people from the bonde of their loyaltie and othe towardes her, and generally to forbid that any man ſhould obey her authoritie, by the which their iudgement they haue open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and playnly declared what other kynges and princes, profeſſyng the Goſpell ſhould looke for at their hands. But what, hath this ſeditious flame conteined it ſelfe within the boundes and limites of Europe. Hath it not burſt out &amp; ouer retched the pillers of
<pb facs="tcp:180997:73"/>
Hercules, hath it not filled the ſhores of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phricke with the dead mens bodyes: hath it not ſtyrred vp the Mores to armour, and the Turke to battaile: hath it not ſhaken the ſcaffold of the whole world with a moſt terrible tempeſt and doth it not alſo now (moſt noble Princes) prepare it ſelfe to burſt out amongeſt you, to arme your ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues agaynſt your owne bowelles if ye take not hede: notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding we do not doubt, but that the Lord for his mercy ſake wil in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due your honors with ſuch wiſedome and courage that you ſhall ſtand and withſtand their miſchieuous practiſes.</p>
            <p>But we (moſt mighty <hi>Ceſar,</hi> and ye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowmed princes of Germany) beſech your your honors not to neglect vs the moſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable of all men,<note place="margin">An earneſt petition to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, and to the princes of germany</note> baniſhed our countrey, ſpoyled of our riches, ſclau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dered with igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, oppreſſed with pouerty, through theyr great and vnſpeakable tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny. Remember that Belgy is a part of Germany, wherof a great part is conteyned within the riuer of Rhene, &amp; a great part alſo by moſt auncient right obeyng to the Emperors lawes, &amp; ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes. Remember that Brabant hath bene alwayes in moſt auncient inheritaunces of the Empire, and the Dukes therof hath in all ages heretofore bounde them ſelues to
<pb facs="tcp:180997:73"/>
the Emperours, to be in theyr retinue and protection. And that Antwerpe is accomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the chief: Marqueſdome of the Empyre, and that <hi>Gueldria, Phriſia,</hi> and the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey <hi>Gormingen, Tranſiſelan,</hi> and <hi>Came<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racenſis,</hi> are all vnder the iuriſdiction of the Empire: and that Hollande, Zelande, Hannony, and other Townes of Belgy haue apperteyned to the dukes of Barrey, as theyr auncetors goodes &amp; inheritaunce. Do not you deſpiſe the frendſhyppe that is betwene vs, by name, toung, and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſocietie, and that we let paſſe all ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guyties. Remember moſt (mighty <hi>Ceſar</hi>) that <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth your fathers brother was lately choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of the middes of Flau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ders to the gouernement of the Empire, as though he had bene by nation a Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane, and that <hi>Maximilian</hi> alſo your great graundfather, did ioyne in alyaunce by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage all the countrey of Belgy, to the moſt noble and auncient houſe of Auſtrice. And that <hi>Charles</hi> the Emperour not long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cauſed that whole prouince to bee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compted as one of the eſtates and limites of the Empire in the Parlament holden at Auguſte, all the eſtates and princes of Ger<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>many aſſentyng thereunto,<note place="margin">1548.</note> and that they might be in the ſauegarde and defence of
<pb facs="tcp:180997:74"/>
the Empire agaynſt all violence and iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. And that they by name haue bene ſent as Embaſſadors to all the aſſemblyes of the Empire from the prouince of Belgye, and that they haue payde tribute requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of them for the repeilyng of the great Turke, and that it is vntill this day contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie whether the Duke of Brabant or the Byſhop of Magdeburge ſhould ſit in hygher roomes at the aſſemblyes, ſo that without all doubte the prouince of lowe Germany ſhould not be accompted as A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenes from the Empire. Do not you ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne (moſt mighty Emperour, and ye noble Princes of Germany) the humble ſuyte of vs your frendes requeſtyng your truſt and ayde agaynſt the outragious cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty of thoſe moſt proude and abhominable men. We do not deny to be obedient to our kyng, to obey hys commaundementes paye our tributes, taſkes, and ſubſidies, whatſoeuer to ſhewe our fayth and loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie towardes hym in all poyntes. But in we moſt humble wiſe do deſire that we may haue our conſcience and Religion left vs fréely, leſt in that laſt iudgement we be found giltie of violatyng the fayth of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt with an vngodly conſcience, and that we may by the good licence of the kyng
<pb facs="tcp:180997:74"/>
defend and kepe the health of our ſoules.</p>
            <p>And we by the Immortall God, and by his onely ſonne Ieſus Chriſt, whoſe name we profeſſe in our publike religion, pray, &amp; beſéech your Maieſties highneſſes, that we may defend our ſelues, our wiues, childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; riches, but aboue all our conſcience fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the pride of the Inquiſitors, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the auarice of the new biſhops, &amp; fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the outragious luſt of the moſt miſcheuous miniſters of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition, and raſcall ſouldiers. And if the frendly name of the Gorgnames can no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing moue you, yet let that moſt ſtraight bond wherwith we ar knit together in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt whoſe members we boaſt our ſelues to be, moue you: let the duety you owe to all mankinde, moue you: let the doubtfull &amp; incertayne condition of mans eſtate, moue you: let crooked old men now wrapt in ſorow, moue you: let miſerable wydowes, vnfortunate orphanes, mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng virgines, let ſo greate and ſo huge a company of miſerable men, moue you: who altogether driuen out of their houſes, throwne from their poſſeſſions, depriued of the commodities of theyr countrey, ſpoyled of al eſtimation, violently plucked from the boſomes of their iuſt carefull parentes, lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing wiues, and tender childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wandring
<pb facs="tcp:180997:75"/>
and ſcattred abroad in ſtraunge countries, not knowing what ſhal become of them, do ſéeke waſt reſting places, ſmall cheare, and libertie of theyr conſcience. But if no occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſhall be offered you, to reſtore vs vnto our countrey agayne, yet geue no eare to our aduerſaries accuſations, nor place to theyr vnſatiable crueltie.</p>
            <p>We know for a certainty, that they will neuer ceaſe to vrge you to depriue vs of all the humanitie and gentlenes, wherewith you entertayned and cheriſhed vs in your countries: ſo that there be neyther ayre left to the liuing, nor earth to the dead, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge to poore exiles. But we pray you moſt noble Princes, to regarde more the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement of God (who commaundeth you to receyue ſtraungers and poore bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed men, not onely wythin your gates or walles but euen in your houſes, and to che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh them wyth all humanitie:) then the commaundementes of a few ſpaniſh prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes, which with the duke of Alba, contend and labour to haue vs the throwne out of your Empyre. Suffer not the feare and terror of the ſpaniſh name to be of more force wyth you, then the name and frendſhip of the Germane. For what ſhould we ſpeake of the agréement of our religion? the which
<pb facs="tcp:180997:75"/>
truely ſhoulde moue you not to ſuffer vs which be ioyned wyth you in the body of Chriſt, in one profeſſion of fayth, in one ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſme, to be by the luſt of a few (which haue no religion but theyr gréedy auarice) baniſhed lyke ſtraungers and enemies, leſt that Chriſt the King of all kinges in that laſt day of iudgement, take that done vnto hymſelf, which is cruelly exerciſed agaynſt vs, being by hys frée grace and mercy vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to his body and made his members: for though they do pretende the difference of our religion, there is no cauſe (moſt noble princes) why you ſhould be moued. For we which do with you acknowledge one God the Father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, true God and very man, one holy Ghoſt: and we which do reſt our ſelues in the onely ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfaction of Ieſus Chriſt, and for hys ſake are baniſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ar countrey, ſpoyled of our goodes, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> appoynted as ſhéepe vnto the ſlaughter: which acknowledge one church, one woorde of God, for the foundation of our health: and laſtly, with you do looke for one reſurrection from the dead, and lyfe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting, geuen by the frée grace and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of God, do not you thinke that we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe any other religion then that which you do. But if we ſhall by the expoſition of
<pb facs="tcp:180997:76"/>
ſome woordes ſéeme to differ, remember that the Apoſtles themſelues, and theyr di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples did neuer ſo fully agree, but there was in ſome thinges a litle diſſention. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menber that euen the auncient fathers of the primitiue church haue not onely left in theyr writinges errors, but alſo in many places open contrarieties: the which true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the déepe prouidence and wiſedome of God, is not without great profite ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted: that we knowing the infirmitie of our owne wit may learne to forſake the iudgement of man, and cleaue onely to the authority of the woord of God: and not to peefer the auctority of man, and our owne iudgment, before the auctority of the word of God: but to beare one an others bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, and with chriſtian charity to couer and wiſely to beare one an others errors, and infirmities. And yet notwithſtandyng what diſcorde of Religion can there be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſt vs, which do not onely embrace the onely word of God, but alſo out of that worde take the forme of our fayth, and all thinges which we vſe in our religion. For we truely do wyth moſt ioyfull hartes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue and embrace the confeſſion which our Auncytors deliuered vp to Charles the Emperour at Auguſta. And if we may
<pb facs="tcp:180997:76"/>
geue our iudgement in any thing, we ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe in all pointes to the doctrine of thoſe Diuines, by whoſe labour that forme of theyr fayth was drawne out: we accompt them not onely as our brethren, but euen for the moſt deuine and excellent prophets of God. And they likewiſe do embrace vs with great and incredible charity, and with all brotherly loue and piety. It is therfore ye Princes a more cauell fayned of our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries, which ſay, that we profeſſe a reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, diuerſe from the Germanes: for they ſtudy nothing els, but that when they haue ſette vs together by the eares, they might teare the members of Chriſt in pée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and ſo oppreſſe vs ſeperated and diſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, whome they were not able to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw, faſt ioyned in amitie.</p>
            <p>But ye men and Princes, whiche haue knowen long agoe their craftes and ſubtel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, be ye not therewith moued, neither ſuffer ye the falſe cauels of our aduerſaryes to haue more power, to teare and diſmem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the members of the body of Chriſt, then the word and commaundement of the ſame Ieſus Chriſt, then the ſincere iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of your Princes and Diuines hath power and force to vnite and knitte vp the ſame. Neither let the diuerſe interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:180997:77" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of one word preuayle more with you, then the moſt ſure and vndoubted conſent of the whole Scripture and fayth. By the whiche fayth and by the moſt holy body of the ſonne Ieſus Chriſt, into the whiche he hath ioyned vs to hym ſelfe with a knot in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſoluble, We ones agayne in moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble wiſe beſech and intreate you, that your charitable mercy, which hath bene alwayes preſt and ready to helpe all poore and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed innocentes, benyngly to receaue vs alſo with ſome tuition and ſafegard, which for the name Ieſus Chriſt do not onely ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer all cruell tormentes, but alſo are ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed with moſt falſe and vniuſt repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and that you would onely as long as it ſhall pleaſe God to chaſten vs thus with exile beyng ſpoyled of all our goodes and commodities of our countrey, with your gentleneſſe ſomewhat to eaſe vs, whom Gods correction doth kéepe low and in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie, ſo ſhall you do an acceptable worke vnto God hym ſelfe the iuſt iudge of all thinges, and ſtyrre vs vp diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to call vpon his mercy and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious fauour for you and your people. Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
